<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "http://www.library.kent.edu/ead.dtd">
<ead>
<eadheader findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="dublin core" repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601">
<eadid mainagencycode="OCX" url="http://ohiolink.edu/EAD/oha.irk.html" countrycode="us">OCX0036</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>Xavier University inactive committees records</titleproper>
<author>Thomas Kennealy,S.J.</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt><publisher>Xavier University Archives and Special Collections</publisher><address><addressline>Xavier University, McDonald Library</addressline><addressline>3800 Victory Parkway</addressline><addressline>Cincinnati, OH 45207</addressline></address><date type="publication">2017</date></publicationstmt></filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded by Tim McCabe using the OhioLINK EAD Application in <date>2014</date></creation>
<langusage>English</langusage>
<descrules>Describing Archives: a Content Standard</descrules>
</profiledesc>
<revisiondesc><change><date normal="2014-09-23">September 23, 2014</date><item>Record modified to reflect changes in holdings.</item></change><change><date normal="2014-12-09">December 9, 2014</date><item>Record modified to show transfer of  Box 1, Folder 10 to XUA-51</item></change></revisiondesc></eadheader>
<archdesc level="collection" type="inventory" relatedencoding="MARC">
<did>
<head>Overview of the Collection</head>
<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
<corpname>Xavier University Archives and Special Collections</corpname>
<address><addressline>Phone: 513-745-4821</addressline>
<addressline>http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives</addressline>
</address>
</repository>
<origination label="Creator:"><corpname encodinganalog="110">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)</corpname></origination>
<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Xavier University inactive committees records</unittitle>
<physdesc label="Extent:" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>1.25 linear feet (3 boxes)</extent></physdesc>
<abstract label="Abstract:" encodinganalog="520$a">This is a collection of committee records of various inactive Xavier University committees. Holdings for individual committees may be fragmented.</abstract>
<unitid encodinganalog="035" label="Accession Number" countrycode="us" repositorycode="OCX">XUA-36</unitid>
<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language:">The records are in <language langcode="eng">English</language></langmaterial>
<physloc label="Location:">Xavier University Archives, Cincinnati, Ohio</physloc><unitdate type="inclusive" label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f" normal="1937/2006" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1937-2006</unitdate></did>
<!-- TOP LEVEL METADATA GOES HERE: -->
<bioghist encodinganalog="545"><head>History of Xavier University inactive committee records</head><p>This is a collection of records from various lesser known discontinued committees at Xavier University. Holdings for individual committees may be limited and fragmented.</p><bioghist/></bioghist><scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a"><head>Scope and Content</head><p>This is a collection of inactive Xavier University committee records. The collection includes records for both ad hoc and standing committees. A number of topics are represented in the assembled documents which are arranged alphabetically by committee name.</p><scopecontent/></scopecontent><arrangement encodinganalog="351$b"><head>Statement of Arrangement</head><p>Records are arranged alphabetically by committee name.</p></arrangement><prefercite encodinganalog="524"><head>Preferred Citation</head><p>Box #, Folder #, XUA-36, Xavier University inactive committees records, Special Collections and Archives, Xavier University, Cincinnati, Ohio.</p></prefercite><controlaccess><head>Indexing Terms</head><p>The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.</p><controlaccess><head>Subjects:</head><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Administration</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Track system (Education)--Ohio</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Planning</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Universities and colleges--Curricula--Catalogs</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Societies</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Curricula</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Multiculturalism--Ohio</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">African Americans--Education (Higher)--Ohio</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Campus planning--Ohio</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Buildings</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Arts--Ohio</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Language and languages--Study and teaching</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Funds and scholarships</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Universities and colleges--Honors courses--Ohio</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Education--Aims and objectives--Ohio</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Finance</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Students--Civil rights--Ohio</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Xavier University (Cincinnati,Ohio)--Students</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Libraries</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Employees</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Competency-based education--Ohio</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Public relations</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Student publications--Ohio</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Research grants</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Research--Ohio</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Schedules, School--Ohio</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Military art and science--Ohio</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">United States--Army--Reserve Officers' Training Corps</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">College students</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Tuition</subject></controlaccess><controlaccess><head>Organizations/Corporations:</head><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Committee</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Advanced Placement Committee</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Alumni Council</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). University Catalogue Committee</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Coordinating Committee</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Council of the College of Arts and Sciences</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Diversity Advisory Committee</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Edgecliff Campus Coordinating Committee</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Facilities Planning Committee</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Fine Arts Committee</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Committee on Foreign Languages in the Xavier Core</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Graduate Scholarship and Fellowship Advisory Committee</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Honors Programs Review Committee</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Committee on Instructional Purposes</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati,Ohio). Interim Executive Academic Committee</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Investment Counseling Committee</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Joint Statement Committee</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Library Planning Committee</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Non-Faculty Salary Committee</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Outcomes Assessment Committee</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). University Planning Committee</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Planning Steering Committee</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Public Relations Committee</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Student Publications Committee</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Committee on Research and Advanced Study</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="lctgm">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Schedule Committee</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Speakers and Programs Committee</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Academic Council. ROTC Subcommittee</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Committee on the Statutes</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Committee on the Study of Academic and Social Life at Xavier</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Committee on Tuition</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Committee on University Purposes</corpname></controlaccess></controlaccess><dsc type="combined"><head>Detailed Description of The Collection</head><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>Administrative Committee</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1967/1986" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1967-1986</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>It is not clear when this committee was created, but it existed during the 1961-62 Academic Year.</p><p>Normally it met every Monday morning during the school year and was sometimes referred to as the Monday Morning Administrators' Meeting. Its name was changed several times over the years and it was discontinued after the meeting of September 25, 1986. Prior to 1975 it was called the Administrative Problems Committee. From 1975 to 1977, it was known as the Administrative Communication Committee. From 1977 to 1986, it   In 1971-72 the committee was described as follows: "The Administrative Problems Committee, appointed and chaired by the president, meets weekly during the school year. Its purpose is to facilitate communication between the various administrative offices of the University. Its membership includes the principal University administrators and a representative of the Faculty Committee." In 1977-78 it was described as follows: "The Administrative Committee is chaired by the president. Consisting of major administrators, a representative of the Faculty Committee and the president of the Student Government, the committee facilitates general communication between the various offices and divisions of the University."</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>Advanced Placement Committee</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1968/1974" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968-1974</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>In 1961 Xavier had an Advanced Placement Committee. It is not known how long the Committee had existed before that. The Committee continued in existence until the end of the 1974-75 Academic Year, when it was apparently discontinued. After that year it no longer appears on the list of the University's standing committees.</p><p>The charge of the committee was as follows: "The Advanced Placement Committee makes recommendations to the Academic Vice President on policies and programs involving the advanced ranking of students wishing to enter the University. Its members include representatives of the academic department which sponsor advanced programs." (See "Descriptions of the XU Committees, 1974-75").</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>Alumni Council</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1974/1984" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974-1984</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>The history of this council is obscure. There is no mention of it in any of the annual lists of the University's Standing Committees available in the archives.</p><p>The first memo in this collection, written by James W. Sassen and dated September 5, 1975, indicates that the Council was created in the fall of 1975. It is not clear when it went out of existence. The charge of the Council is not clear. In president Charles Currie's memo to the members of the Alumni Council dated March 29, 1984, he says that the purpose of each of the Council's subcommittees is "to review what is happening in a particular area (of the University) and to offer advice, criticism and suggestions."</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">4</container><unittitle>Catalogue Committee</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1966" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1966</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>It is not certain when this committee was first created or when it went out of existence.  It seems never to have appeared on the annual list of the university's standing committees.</p><p>It met several times in 1966-67 and the minutes of two of those meetings are the only record we have of its existence. The committees' purpose was to revise, correct and update the University course catalogue from year to year.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">5</container><unittitle>Coordinating Committee</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1937/1942" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1937-1942</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>In a letter he wrote on June 5, 1937, Edward VonderHaar, Xavier's Director of Publicity, speaks of the Coordinating Committee as having just been created. It seems to have been discontinued during the Second World War and was not revived afterwards.</p><p>It was made up of representatives of the organizations affiliated with Xavier University and St. Xavier High School.  At one point, it was suggested that the Jesuit Retreat League be asked to join.  This does not seem to have happened.    According to its constitution the object of the committee "shall be to bring together the various associations affiliated with Xavier University and St. Xavier High School for mutual cooperation and the more effective furthering of activities inaugurated by one or more of the several associations the better to promote Jesuit education."  In particular, the committee was to prevent conflicts in the scheduling of activities and events.  Its members were drawn from friends, alums and administrators of both institutions.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">6</container><unittitle>Council of the College of Arts and Sciences</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1973/1975" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1973-1975</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>The Council of the College of Arts and Sciences was created at the beginning of the 1972-73 academic year and was discontinued at the end of the 1980-81 academic year.</p><p>Its official name was the Council of the College of Arts and Sciences, but was occasionally referred as the Arts and Sciences Council - Planning Board.    The committee's charge in 1973-74 was: "...The purpose of the Council is to study new courses and programs proposed by various departments, to encourage inter-departmental cooperation, and to initiate changes in curriculum." In 1980-81, the charge read:  "Included in its responsibilities are the study of new programs and the development of new curricula.  The chair of the Council is the Dean."</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">7</container><unittitle>Diversity Advisory Committee</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2003 July 31" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2003 July 31</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>The Diversity Advisory Committee was created by President Michael J. Graham, S.J. probably sometime in 2002.  It submitted is final report on July 31, 2003.</p><p>Dr. Kenneth B. Durgans and Dr. Janice Walker served as co-chairs.  The committee was created to "develop a comprehensive plan for Xavier University which will establish promoting diversity as a core value of the institution....recommend implementation of strategies created by the Diversity Advisory Committee....focus immediate efforts on issues pertaining to the number and participation of African Americans and African Diaspora in the Xavier University community which includes all internal and external constituents....routinely evaluate components of the plan and related strategies based upon that evaluation and then revise the plan and strategies accordingly." (Committee's Final Report)</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">8</container><unittitle>Edgecliff Campus Coordinating Committee</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1984/1986" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1984-1986</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>Originally known as the Edgecliff Committee, this committee was created in July, 1984.  It ceased to exist sometime after February, 1986, when Xavier sold the Edgecliff property.</p><p>It had several different names in the course of its history, but the Edgecliff Campus Coordinating Committee was the most common. In 1985-86, the annual list of committees described the charge of the committee as follows:  "The purpose of this committee is to insure that articulation and communication between the Edgecliff and Avondale campuses remains effective and that the specific needs of the Edgecliff Campus are responded to."  The committee was divided into two parts, the Operations subcommittee and the Policy subcommittee.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">9</container><unittitle>Facilities Planning Committee</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1986/1988" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1986-1988</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>At a meeting which it held on November 26, 1986, the Executive Committee decided that the responsibilities of the Rainbo Task Force should be broadened and that the committee should be renamed the Facilities Planning Committee.</p><p>Dr. Richard Hirte', the Vice President of Financial Administration, was appointed first chair.  The committee was discontinued sometime around 2005.  According to a memo from President Albert DiUlio, S.J., to Dr. Robert Murray, dated December 2, 1986, "The first charge of the Facilities Planning Committee is twofold:   1.     To assess the existing time and space resources on the Xavier campus (excluding the Rainbo property). 2.     To develop a short-term contingency plan to fully utilize existing resources to accommodate a move of all course offerings and personnel from the Edgecliff campus to the Xavier campus by summer, 1987.  As of 2001-02, the committee's charge was as follows:  "The Facilities Planning Committee assists the President with major University facility planning by identifying space and facility needs, locating resources, and recommending alternative solutions."</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">10</container><unittitle>Fine Arts Committee</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1950/1959" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1950-1959</unitdate><physloc>The contents of this folder have been transferred to XUA-51, Xavier University Fine Arts Committee records</physloc></did><bioghist><p>According to the annual University Lists of Standing Committees, the Fine Arts Committee was created sometime prior to 1961 and was discontinued at the end of the 1968-69 academic year.     It was reinstated at the beginning of the 1972-73 school year and was permanently dropped after the 1983-84 year. In 1973-74 the charge read as follows:  "Appointed annually by the President and electing its own chairman, the Fine Arts Committee makes recommendations to the Vice President for Student Development on fine arts programs and exhibitions." In 1980-81 the charge read as follows:  "This committee has as its purpose to develop interest in the fine arts in the community and to draw up recommendations regarding fine arts, the Carriage House Gallery, art exhibits, the care, storing and sale of paintings and other artistic objects belonging to the University." (Annual Lists of University Standing Committees)</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">11</container><unittitle>Foreign Languages in the Xavier Core Ad Hoc Committee</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1979 February-June" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1979 February-June</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>In early 1979, the Board of Undergraduate Studies instructed the dean of the College of Arts and Sciences, Joseph T. Angilella, S.J., to form an ad hoc committee to study the role of foreign languages in the core curriculum at Xavier.</p><p>The committee, chaired by Dr. Karl Wentersdorf, professor of English, consisted of four faculty members and one student. It began its deliberations in February, 1979, and submitted its final report in June of that same year. The report was then delivered to the Board of Undergraduate Studies for its review on August 13, 1979. The charge of the committee was "to study the role of foreign languages in the core curriculum at Xavier." (See the 8/13/1979 memo of committee members to the academic administrators.)</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">12</container><unittitle>Graduate Scholarship and Fellowship Advisory Committee</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1956/1973" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1956-1973</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>This committee was in existence in 1963 under the title of the Graduate Scholarship Advisory Committee. However, it first appeared on the annual list of the University standing committees in 1966-67 under the name of the Graduate Scholarship and Fellowship Advisory Committee.</p><p>The committee was discontinued at the end of the 1975-76 academic year.   According to the annual list of standing committees for 1971-72, the charge of this committee was as follows:  "The Committee on Graduate Scholarships and Fellowships, appointed annually by the Provost, Robert Mulligan, S.J., makes recommendations to the undergraduate deans and to the Academic Vice President as to the manner in which Xavier undergraduates may be best assisted in obtaining scholarships and fellowships for graduate work."</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">13</container><unittitle>Honors Program Review Committee</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1991/1992" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1991-1992</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>This ad hoc committee was created by the Academic Vice President, Dr. Joan Connell, in March, 1991.</p><p>For a list of the persons who served on it, see page 1 of the final report.  The committee met for the last time on May 7, 1992, when it unanimously approved its final report.  The final report was then published on May 19, 1992.   The committee was charged with the task of reviewing the Honors Programs at Xavier University and make recommendations concerning them.  At the time, there were two Honors Programs, the Honors Bachelor of Arts Program and the University Scholars' Program.  For further information concerning the committee's charge, see page 2 of the Final Report.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">14</container><unittitle>Committee on Instructional Purposes</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1955/1959" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1955-1959</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>In early March, 1957, President Paul L. O'Connor, S.J., acting on the suggestion of the Academic Council, appointed a committee "to recommend how we can best study the purposes of our instructional program.  Eventually we want a full statement of our objectives that will serve to guide curricular decisions and stimulate improvement of instruction." (Memo by Rev. Henry Wirtenberger, S.J., dated March 8, 1957)</p><p>The work of this committee began in March 1957 and ended in March 1959.  While this committee functioned independently of Xavier's preparations for the 1958 visitation by the North Central Association, it clearly played a role in Xavier's self-study prior to the visit.  The committee is sometimes referred to as Instructional Purposes Committee and sometimes The Evaluation Committee.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">15</container><unittitle>Interim Executive Academic Committee</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1985" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1985</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>In early August, 1985, Dr. John Minahan resigned from the position of Academic Vice President.  To fill this office President Charles Currie, S. J., established the Interim Executive Academic Committee (IEAC) composed of Charles Cusick the Dean of the College of Arts and Sciences, Roger Fortin, Associate Vice President for academic affairs, and Francis Mastrianna, Dean of the College of Business Administration.  The triumvirate, or troika, as the IEAC was called, assumed the responsibilities assigned to the office of the Academic Vice President as specified in the XU Faculty Handbook.  The Interim Executive Academic Committee was discontinued in the summer of 1986 when Dr. Robert Murray, professor of Classics, was appointed acting Academic Vice President for one year.  In June 1987, Dr. Joan Connell became Academic Vice President.  (Fortin's history of Xavier, pages 312 to 317) The committee assumed "the responsibilities assigned to the Office of the Academic Vice President in the Faculty Handbook, page 4".  (Memo to Faculty and Administration from Charles L. Currie, S. J. dated August 29, 1985.)</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">16</container><unittitle>Investment Counseling Committee</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1971 September 15" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1971 September 15</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>This committee seems to have been created in September, 1971, at the suggestion of Mr. Bert Reynold.  It consisted of 8 persons including the president and the financial vice president of the University.  It is not known when the committee was discontinued.   The following information on the charge of the committee is taken from the minutes of the committee's meeting on September 15, 1971:  "For a number of years, Mr. Bert Reynold has on a voluntary basis been acting as an investment counsel to the University. On several occasions he has suggested an advisory committee that would serve as a broader base for policy decisions.  The present committee will meet this need.  Meeting regularly, it will advise on general policy and, from time to time, individual members would be called upon for advice on particular action".</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">17</container><unittitle>Joint Statement Committee (Rights and Freedoms of Students)</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1969/1971" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1969-1971</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>In 1967 this committee was created to produce a university statement on the rights and freedoms of students at Xavier University. In late July, 1970, the committee submitted a proposed text to President Paul L. O'Connor, S.J., entitled "Joint Statement of Rights and Freedoms of Students for Xavier University". The document was eventually approved by the Board of Trustees.  Subsequently, the Joint Statement Committee became a standing committee of the university.     The original Joint Statement Committee was charged with the task of writing the Joint Statement of Student Rights and Freedoms.  After that, the standing Joint Statement Committee had the "responsibility of regularly reviewing the officially approved University statement on student rights and for proposing additions or emendations to the statement.  Its chairman is appointed by the Provost".  (Descriptions of Committees, 1971-72).  The committee seems to have been discontinued at the end of 1974-75 academic year.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">18</container><unittitle>Library Planning Committee</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2002/2003" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002-2003</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>This committee was created in late 2002 and continued its work until sometime in the middle of 2003 when it apparently went out of existence.  It seems to have been an ad hoc committee. In a document dated January 9, 2003 and titled "Library Planning Committee:  Project Charter", the committee's goal was "to explain the Library Vision Statement in operational terms".  The committee was to "articulate the design and service expectations for Xavier University's library."  The ultimate goal was to identify the service and space needs "of a new facility" which will then be interpreted by an architectural design consultant</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">19</container><unittitle>Non-Faculty Salary Committee</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1971" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1971</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>It is not clear when this committee was created or when it was discontinued.  It is mentioned in the annual list of the University standing committees for the years 1961-62 and 1964-65, but for no other years.  The course catalogues do not mention it at all.  The few documents in this collection are dated 1971.  There seems to be no other information available about its meetings or business. According to the memo written by Thomas W. Gehner dated April 2, 1971, this committee had the responsibility of reviewing the current salary ranges for all staff employees, and made recommendations to the Board of Trustees concerning the salary ranges for the following year.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">20</container><unittitle>Outcomes Assessment Committee</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1993 June" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1993 June</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>The Outcomes Assessment Committee was formed in November, 1991, and met almost weekly during the 1992-93 academic year to develop a plan for assessing student academic achievement at Xavier University.  The committee submitted its final report in June, 1993, and went out of existence.  For more information on how this committee's recommendations were implemented, consult the archives boxes labeled PLANS FOR ASSESSMENT OF STUDENT ACADEMIC ACHIEVEMENT 1993-2007 FOR THE HIGHER LEARNING COMMISSION OF THE NORTH CENTRAL ASSOCIATION. (3 boxes)   Sometime in the late 2000s a new committee named the Academic Assessment and Planning Committee was created and was still listed as a standing committee during the 2013-14 academic year.   "The North Central Association's requirement for documentation of student academic achievement reflects a national initiative as public official demand greater accountability from colleges and universities.  The Outcomes Assessment Committee, in November, 1991, initiated as eighteen month process of developing a model for assessment of student achievement and quality improvement within the Division of Academic Affairs at Xavier University." (Committee's Final Report, page ii)</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">21</container><unittitle>University Planning Committee</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1985 May 1" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1985 May 1</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>"Building on President Charles Currie's initial planning efforts, in the fall of 1984 the university established a University Planning Committee.  Co-chaired by Frank Hoenemeyer of the Board of Trustees and Dr. John Minahan, the Academic Vice President, the committee consisted of administrators, faculty, students, alumni, and friends of the university."  The committee completed its work in December, 1984, and submitted its final report sometime in 1985. The committee was "charged to review the strengths, weaknesses, opportunities and threats (SWOT) of each university department."  (Fortin's history, page 301)</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">22</container><unittitle>Planning Steering Committee All Committee Reports: Integration of the Strategic Plan (Draft)</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2003 June" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2003 June</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the document "All Committee Reports" of June, 2003. These are the reports of the ten task forces or groups created by the Planning Steering Committee. The document includes the introductory chapter "Integration of the Strategic Plan, June, 2003 (Draft)."</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>"In March, 2002, President Graham established the Planning Steering Committee, chaired by Dr. Ronald Slepitza...   The committee involved 23 members of the faculty, administration, staff and student body.... Under Slepitza's direction, a whole set of task forces...launched out in several directions... The groups included the Library Planning Committee, Teaching, Learning and Technology Committee, Career Development and Lifelong Learning Committee and 7 others.  Over time a smaller work group weaved together the various individual reports into a more coherent whole."  (Fortin's history of Xavier, pages 380-381)    The committee was charged with "the responsibility of overseeing the university's multiple activities... with respect to planning".  (Fortin, page 380) Each of the committee's task forces had its own specific charge which can be found in the final report of each task force.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">23</container><unittitle>Planning Steering Committee All Committee Reports</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2003" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2003</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the document "All Committee Reports" dated June, 2003.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>"In March, 2002, President Graham established the  Planning Steering Committee, chaired by Dr. Ronald Slepitza...   The  committee involved 23 members of the faculty, administration, staff and  student body.... Under Slepitza's direction, a whole set of task  forces...launched out in several directions... The groups included the  Library Planning Committee, Teaching, Learning and Technology Committee,  Career Development and Lifelong Learning Committee and 7 others.  Over  time a smaller work group weaved together the various individual reports  into a more coherent whole."  (Fortin's history of Xavier, pages  380-381)    The committee was charged with "the responsibility of  overseeing the university's multiple activities... with respect to  planning".  (Fortin, page 380) Each of the committee's task forces had  its own specific charge which can be found in the final report of each  task force.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">24</container><unittitle>Public Relations Committee</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1940/1948" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1940-1948</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>It is unclear when this committee was created and when it was discontinued. It was in existence during the 1940s, though it may not have met during the years of the Second World War.  It is sometimes referred to as the "Committee on Public Relations", other times as the "Public Relations Council", and more often as "The Public Relations Committee".    The purpose of the committee is not altogether clear from its minutes.  The catalogues of the period do not explain its charge.  In a general way, it tried to promote the university by advertising it, working to increase its enrollment and raise money among other things.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">25</container><unittitle>Publications Committee</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1970" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1970</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>According to the annual lists of standing committees, the Publications Committee was created at the beginning of the 1968-69 academic year and continued to exist until approximately 1998, although its name and mandate changed several times.  In 1972-73, it became the Programs and Publications Committee.  In 1982-83 the name was changed to the Student Programs and Publications Committee. In 1985-86 the name became the Student Publications Committee.  It disappeared from the list of committees around 1998. 
   CHARGE OF THE COMMITTEE:
 
   In 1972 its charge was as follows.  "The committee regularly reviews University publications and makes recommendation regarding general policy as well as evaluations of particular issues.  Its student members are nominated by the Student Senate." (Taken from the annual list of standing committees, 1972-73)
   In 1973 its charge was:  "The duties of the committee include the review and interpretation of University policy in reference to student publications and programs, and the review of applications for editors-in-chief of all student publications." (From the annual list of standing committees, 1973-74)
   In 1992 its charge was:  "The Committee works with the editors of the Xavier Newswire and Musketeer Annual to develop editorial policy, to provide regular feedback on content of publications and to select the editor-in-chief of each publication." (From the annual committee list, 1992-93."</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">26</container><unittitle>Committee on Research and Advanced Study</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1952/1964" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1952-1964</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>It is not known when this committee was created.  It was in existence in 1958 with Dr. Harvey A. Dube as its chair.  The last memo pertaining to its business is dated 1964.  It seems to have been discontinued sometime shortly thereafter. The following is taken from a statement dated January, 1960, entitled RESEARCH POLICIES AND PROCEDURES.  "The Committee on Research and Advanced Study (CRAS) of Xavier University is commissioned to develop the basic items of a program for research and advanced study. These items include: 
1.        Provision for in-service research.
2.        Provision for leave of absence to engage in research and advanced study.
3.        Inquiry into and adoption of various measures to encourage faculty members to engage in research and advanced study.
4.        Provision for University use of this research and advanced study for the purpose of stimulating further scholarly activity."</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">27</container><unittitle>Schedule Committee</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1964/1966" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1964-1966</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>The Schedule Committee was an ad hoc committee created in the spring of 1964 by the Academic Council. It met for the first time on June 29, 1964. Russell J. Walker served as chair. The last papers pertaining to the committee are dated 1966. The Academic Council probably discontinued it shortly thereafter. The committee's mandate was to devise a new system for the scheduling of undergraduate classes. Such questions as the times and days of classes and the number of classes that would be needed were discussed. The committee also raised a number of questions about the University's academic calendar.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">28</container><unittitle>Speakers and Programs Committee</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1961" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1961</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1969" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1969</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>According to the annual lists of university committees the Speakers and Programs Committee came into existence at the beginning of the 1968-69 Academic Year. It disappeared from the annual lists at the end of the 1971-72 year. There was a Programs and Publications Committee from 1972 to 1998, but whether this committee replaced or assumed the responsibilities of the Speakers and Programs Committee is not clear. The charge of the committee as of 1971-72 was the following: "Reporting to the Vice President for Student Affairs, the Speakers Program Committee develops general policy recommendations concerning speakers on campus and, upon request from the Vice President, makes recommendations concerning individual speakers and particular programs being considered to appear on campus." (See XU Committee Descriptions, 1971-72)</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">29</container><unittitle>ROTC Subcommittee of the Academic Council</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1968/1970" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968-1970</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>The Academic Council, which became the Board of Undergraduate Studies in the fall of 1972, created an ad hoc subcommittee in 1968 to review and make recommendations concerning the future of the university's ROTC program. The committee submitted its final report to the Council on February 7, 1969 and, then, went out of existence.    "This subcommittee was established by the Academic Council for the purpose of assembling relevant data for use in the formulation of decisions affecting the future status of the ROTC program at Xavier University....  The fundamental alternatives to consider are whether to drop the ROTC program from the curriculum or to retain a ROTC program in some form on the XU campus." (Final report of the subcommittee, page 1)</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">30</container><unittitle>Committee on the Statutes (of the University)</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1954/1955" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1954-1955</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>The president of Xavier, James F. Maguire, S.J., announced the creation of this committee in a memo to Paul L. O'Connor, S. J., the chair of the committee.  The memo was dated August 19, 1954.  The committee met through much of the 1954-55 academic year.  Its final report, a revised version of the University's statutes, was published on June 1, 1955. The committee was created to revise the Xavier University statutes "as quickly as possible".</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">31</container><unittitle>Committee for the Study of Academic and Social Life at Xavier</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1971" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1971</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>Sometime in 1970 this committee, made up of 5 members of the faculty in the department of psychology and chaired by Vytautas J. Bieliauskas, was created to study the academic and social life on the Xavier campus. It is not clear who established the committee or to whom the final report was submitted.  All aspects of campus life from academic standards, faculty and library to student government and intervisitation were examined.  The principal instrument employed by the committee was a questionnaire that was developed, distributed and analyzed by the committee. The committee was asked to investigate all aspects of student life on the XU campus and to access the students' attitudes toward campus life.  It was also asked to make recommendations for the future.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">32</container><unittitle>Committee on Tuition</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1968/1969" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968-1969</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>This committee was created by President Paul O'Connor, S. J., in November, 1968. It was apparently an ad hoc committee which was never listed among the standing committees of the University and which seems to have gone out of existence at the end of the 1968-69 academic year.  Its chair was Victor B. Nieporte, S. J. Fr. O'Connor spelled out the charge of this committee in the following way:    "I would like the above named to form a committee to study the question of a possible tuition increase for September, 1969....  The study is to be made as part of our Long Range Plan Study which is now underway.  Consequently, your study might also include recommendations for tuition increases during the next five years."  (Memo of President O'Connor dated November 15, 1968)</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">33</container><unittitle>Committee on University Institutional Purposes</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1945/1946" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1945-1946</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>This committee was apparently established by the Academic Council in 1945. It is not known when it ceased to function. The committee submitted a report to the Academic Council dated December 13, 1946. Whether this was its final report is not clear. This committee was apparently set up ty the Academic Council to investigate whether the "curricular departments' were functioning according to the provisions of the University statutes and, if not, what changes should be made.</p></bioghist></c01></dsc></archdesc>
</ead>