<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "http://www.library.kent.edu/ead.dtd">
<ead>
<eadheader findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="dublin core" repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601">
<eadid mainagencycode="OCX" url="http://ohiolink.edu/EAD/oha.irk.html" countrycode="us">OCX0054</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>Finding aid for the Xavier University Campus Buildings and Properties collection</titleproper>
<author>Finding aid prepared by Thomas P. Kennealy, S.J.</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt><publisher>Xavier University Archives and Special Collections</publisher><address><addressline>Xavier University, McDonald Library</addressline><addressline>3800 Victory Parkway</addressline><addressline>Cincinnati, OH 45207</addressline></address><date type="publication">2017</date></publicationstmt></filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded by Tim McCabe using the OhioLINK EAD Application in <date>2014</date></creation>
<langusage>English</langusage>
<descrules>Describing Archives: a Content Standard</descrules>
</profiledesc>
<revisiondesc><change><date normal="2015-04-30">April 30, 2015</date><item>Materials added to the collection.</item></change></revisiondesc></eadheader>
<archdesc level="collection" type="inventory" relatedencoding="MARC">
<did>
<head>Overview of the Collection</head>
<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
<corpname>Xavier University Archives and Special Collections</corpname>
<address><addressline>Phone: 513-745-4821</addressline>
<addressline>http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives</addressline>
</address>
</repository>
<origination label="Creator:"><corpname encodinganalog="110">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)</corpname></origination>
<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Xavier University Campus Buildings and Properties collection</unittitle>
<physdesc label="Extent:" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>8 linear feet (17 boxes)</extent></physdesc>
<abstract label="Abstract:" encodinganalog="520$a">This is collection includes information on the various buildings and properties held by Xavier University. Files may contain correspondence, brochures, newspaper clippings, dedication programs, and other types of materials.</abstract>
<unitid encodinganalog="035" label="Accession Number" countrycode="us" repositorycode="OCX">XUA-54</unitid>
<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language:">The records are in <language langcode="eng">English</language></langmaterial>
<physloc label="Location:">Xavier University Archives, Cincinnati, Ohio</physloc><unitdate type="inclusive" label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f" normal="1920/2012" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1920-2012</unitdate></did>
<!-- TOP LEVEL METADATA GOES HERE: -->
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a"><head>Scope and Content</head><p>This collection consists of correspondence, documents, brochures, minutes of meetings, photos, diagrams and other materials pertaining to the buildings, halls, houses, centers and other properties on the Xavier campus.</p><scopecontent><p>The collection includes information on buildings currently in existence, some buildings that have been razed and a few proposed buildings that were never constructed. It also includes documentation concerning the closing of some streets by the City of Cincinnati in and around the campus. It does not include any of the buildings that St. Xavier College occupied in downtown Cincinnati prior to 1919. For information on the Sycamore Street buildings, consult a separate collection dealing with the Nineteenth Century St. Xavier College and Church.</p><p>In addition, this collection does not include information on any shrines, statues, monuments, fountains or permanent plaques. These materials are found in a separate collection found in the Xavier Archives.</p></scopecontent></scopecontent><arrangement encodinganalog="351$b"><head>Statement of Arrangement</head><p>This collection is arranged alphabetically by the name of the building or property.</p></arrangement><relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544 1"><head>Related Material</head><p>Other materials of related interest can be found in other collections, such as XUA-53, Xavier University Master Building Plans collection. Please contact the archives staff.</p></relatedmaterial><accessrestrict encodinganalog="506"><head>Restrictions on Access</head><p>Some parts of this collection may have restricted access. Please contact the Xavier University Archives staff.</p></accessrestrict><prefercite encodinganalog="524"><head>Preferred Citation</head><p>Box Number, Folder Number, XUA-54, Campus Buildings and Properties collection, Special Collections and Archives, Xavier University, Cincinnati, Ohio.</p></prefercite><accruals encodinganalog="584"><head>Accruals</head><p>Additions to this collection are expected.</p></accruals><controlaccess><head>Indexing Terms</head><p>The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.</p><controlaccess><head>Subjects:</head><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">College buildings--Ohio--Cincinnati</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">College buildings--Designs and plans</subject></controlaccess><controlaccess><head>Organizations/Corporations:</head><corpname encodinganalog="610$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)-- Buildings</corpname></controlaccess></controlaccess><dsc type="combined"><head>Detailed Description of The Collection</head><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>Albers Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1943" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1943</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" 1950" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1950</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. The program for the rededication of the Hall, June 7, 1950; 2. Floor Plans of the Hall; 3. Brochures pertaining to the installation of the hall elevator.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>Albers Hall is located on the west side of the Academic Mall between Hinkle Hall and Logan Hall. It was named in honor of William H. Albers, the principal donor. Built at a cost of $244,000.00, the hall was dedicated on November 10, 1929. Originally the Biology department was found on the third floor, with the Physics and Mathematics departments on the second. Classrooms and the President's office were found on the first floor. Later the Biology department took over the entire building.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>Alter Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1959/1960" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1959-1960</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. Announcements of the new classroom building, Alter Hall; 2. Correspondence pertaining to the construction of Alter Hall; 3. Memorial possibilities in the new Alter Hall; 4. Groundbreaking (May 16, 1959); 5. Dedication Planning Committee documents; 6. Dedication ceremony (December 4, 1960).</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>Alter Hall (the Alter Classroom Building) is located on the east side of the Academic Mall between Bellarmine Chapel and the McDonald Library. It was named in honor of Karl J. Alter, the Archbishop of Cincinnati. Built at a cost of $1,175,000.00, the groundbreaking ceremony took place on May 16, 1959. It was dedicated and blessed by Archbishop Alter on December 4, 1960. The facility opened for classes on February 1, 1961.</p><p>Alter Hall originally contained 32 classrooms, Kelly Auditorium (which seated about 300) and the offices of the Deans, Academic Vice President, Registrar, Evening School, Graduate College and some departmental chairs. Classroom use closed in 2012 for extensive renovation which actually began in 2014. Reopening is planned for September, 2015.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>Alter Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1961" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1961</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" 2010-2014" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 2010-2014</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. Open House inspections of the new Alter Hall; 2. Articles pertaining to the construction of Alter Hall; 3. Memos pertaining to the renovation of Alter Hall which took place between 2006 and 2014; 4. Photos and drawings of Alter Hall from the early 1960's.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">4</container><unittitle>Alumni Center</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2000" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2000</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" 2002" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 2002</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains brochures and newspaper clippings concerning the Alumni Center.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>Alumni Center is located on the south side of Dana Avenue. It was constructed as the Coca-Cola Bottling works and opened on November 28, 1938. In 1986, F&amp;W Publications purchased the property and renovated it. The building was placed on the National Register of Historic Places in 1986. In 2001, Xavier University bought the building and began another extensive renovation. As of 2014, the facility houses the Xavier Office of Physical Plant, the library annex, and a number of other offices, including University Relations.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">5</container><unittitle>Armory</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1947/1948" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1947-1948</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains correspondence, brochures, sketches and photographs concerning the Armory.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>The Armory is located on Winding Way on the West Campus. The original cost of the building was $175,000.00. The cornerstone ceremony took place on June 9, 1948, with Kenneth C. Royall, the Secretary of the United States Army, laying the cornerstone.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">6</container><unittitle>Barracks Buildings</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains one publicity item about the Barracks.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>The "Barracks" were buildings used as student housing after World War II. Ten former Army barrack buildings were brought to campus and re-erected on university property fronting on Ledgewood and Herald Avenues in October, 1946. These barracks accommodated 24 students per building (3 to a room), for a total occupancy of 240. They were razed around 1953. In addition, another barracks was erected between the University Drive and Victory Parkway. It was called North Hall and provided classroom space. Early in 1947, yet another barracks was erected opposite Alumni Science Hall (now Edgecliff Hall), near the entrance to the University Drive. It was called South Hall and served as a snack bar and a theater. Both North Hall and South Hall have been subsequently razed.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>Bellarmine Chapel</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1930/2004" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1930-2004</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. Correspondence, newspaper articles, and a history of the Chapel; 2. Directories and Family Quick Listings of Chapel members.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>St. Robert Bellarmine Chapel was canonically established as a parish by John T. McNicholas, the Archbishop of Cincinnati, in 1927. It was located on the first floor of the Schmidt Library building and served as both a student chapel and archdiocesan parish. The "new" Bellarmine Chapel was dedicated and blessed by Karl J. Alter, Archbishop of Cincinnati, on December 16, 1962. The chapel is named in honor of St. Robert Bellarmine, Jesuit theologian and saint. The new chapel also honors the memory of Charles F. and Elizabeth Williams whose five children were the principal donors. The original cost of the "new" chapel was $364,000.00.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>Bellarmine Chapel</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1961/1962" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1961-1962</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains materials on: 1. Groundbreaking ceremony of the "new" chapel, (May 13, 1961); 2. Laying of the cornerstone of the "new" chapel (September 26, 1962); 3. Dedication of the chapel (December 16, 1962).</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>Bellarmine Chapel</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1961/2006" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1961-2006</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains materials on: 1. Dedication of the St. Robert Bellarmine statue (June 15, 1969); 2. Rededication of the chapel (September 13, 1998); 3. Bellarmine Chapel annual "Steward Reports;" 4. Photos and brochures.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">4</container><unittitle>Boylan Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1974" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains limited correspondence concerning Boylan Hall.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>Boylan Hall was originally a family residence on Ledgewood Avenue next to Bellarmine Chapel. Purchased by the university, it was named in honor of the Rev. Murtha Boylan, S.J., professor of psychology for many years. In the 1960s it housed the office of the Assistant to the President as well as faculty offices. In the early 1970s it served as the Undergraduate Recruitment and Admission Office. It was razed in the late 1970s to make room for Hailstones Hall.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">5</container><unittitle>Breen Lodge</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2011" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains notes concerning the history of Breen Lodge written by the Xavier Archives staff.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>Breen Lodge, located on Ledgewood Drive across from Brockman Hall, was originally a residential house used by Xavier Jesuits. Subsequently it was used by various campus groups including its use as a women's center at Xavier. It was probably named to honor the Rev. Aloysius A. Breen, S.J., who was the treasurer of Xavier University at one time.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">6</container><unittitle>Brockman Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1950/1954" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1950-1954</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. A brochure announcing the construction of Brockman Hall; 2. Correspondence pertaining to the construction and naming of Brockman Hall; 3. A brochure about gift opportunities.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>This building was named in honor of the Rev. Hubert F. Brockman, S.J., president of Xavier from 1923 to 1931. The original cost of the building was $915,000.00. Groundbreaking took place on May 16, 1953. Its dedication and blessing occurred on May 21, 1955. Myers Y. Cooper, former Governor of Ohio, eulogized Fr. Brockman on this occasion.The dedication of the St. Francis Xavier mural in the Brockman Hall lounge happened on May 18, 1957. The dedication of the Mackentepe Memorial Lounge was on June 9, 1959.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">7</container><unittitle>Brockman Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1953/1959" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1953-1959</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains information on the following: 1. Groundbreaking ceremony; 2. Dedication and blessing ceremony; 3. Dedication of the St. Francis Xavier mural; 4. Dedication of the Mackentepe Memorial Lounge.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">8</container><unittitle>Brockman Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1973" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1973</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains information about a proposed, but never built, swimming pool for Brockman Hall.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>Cintas Center</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1993/1996" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1993-1996</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains brochures about the Convocation Center (later called the Cintas Center) and some Convocation Center planning documents.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>The Cintas is Xavier University's athletic facility. In addition to providing the basketball arena for the university team, this building houses the Athletic Department and other campus offices.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>Cintas Center</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1997" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1997</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains memos, meeting notes, and other items concerning the planning of the Convocation Center.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>Cintas Center</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1998" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1998</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the document "Site Specific Health and Safety Plan: The Cintas Center, Xavier University....Prepared for Xavier University, May 8, 1998." Other materials are included.</p></scopecontent><accessrestrict><p>Some materials may have restricted access. Please contact the archives staff.</p></accessrestrict><userestrict/></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">4</container><unittitle>Cintas Center</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1999/2000" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1999-2000</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains memorandums, contractor lists and the commemorative section by Cincinnati Magazine entitled "Cintas Center: a View Inside the Spectacular Cintas Center at Xavier University."</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">5</container><unittitle>Cintas Center</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2000" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2000</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains information on the relationship of Xavier University to the City of Norwood about the Cintas Center.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">4</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>Cintas Center</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2001/2003" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001-2003</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains marketing brochures, a catering guide, testimonial letters and other items about the Cintas Center.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">4</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>Cintas Center</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1997/2002" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1997-2002</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains newspaper articles about the Cintas Center.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">4</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>Cintas Center</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2001/2005" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001-2005</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains overview information about the Cintas Center. Also included is the document "Cintas Center: the First Five Years."</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">4</container><container type="Folder">4</container><unittitle>Cohen Center</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1978/1989" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978-1989</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder includes a Cohen Center fact sheet as well as correspondence.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>The A.B. Cohen Center was formerly the 18 acre Norwood facility of the U.S. Shoe Corporation on Cleneay Avenue. It was gifted to Xavier University in November, 1978. In 1987, after extensive renovation, the Center became the home of the Departments of Art, Nursing, and Hospital and Health Administration.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">4</container><container type="Folder">5</container><unittitle>Cohen Center</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1978" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1978</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" 1980" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1980</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains a 1978 U.S. Shoe Annual Report and also documents concerning a 1980 lawsuit concerning the U.S. Shoe property.</p></scopecontent><accessrestrict><p>This folder may have restricted access. Please contact the archives staff.</p></accessrestrict></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">4</container><container type="Folder">6</container><unittitle>Cohen Center</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1979" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1979</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains documents relating to the 1980 lawsuit involving the Cohen property.</p></scopecontent><accessrestrict><p>This folder may have restricted access. Please contact the archives staff.</p></accessrestrict></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">5</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>Conaton Learning Commons</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2010" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2010</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains some brochures about the Conaton Learning Commons and the speakers program for the grand opening of the facility.</p></scopecontent><relatedmaterial><p>For more information on the construction of this building, consult XUA-53, the Xavier University Master Building Plans collection.</p></relatedmaterial><bioghist><p>The Conaton Learning Commons was named to honor Michael J. Conaton,  Class of 1955, chair of the Xavier Board of Trustees (1985-2004), and  one-time acting president. The naming was at the request of Charles P.  Gallagher, 1960 graduate. Mr. Gallagher's generous gift helped to build  this state of the art facility. The Conaton Learning Commons is part of  the James E. Hoff, S.J. Academic Quadrangle project. It opened on July  20, 2010.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">5</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>Corcoran Football Field</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1927/1968" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1927-1968</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains correspondence, blueprints and some news clippings pertaining to this facility.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>The west side of the field, with a seating capacity of 3,750, was completed and dedicated on October 22, 1921. The east side was completed and dedicated on November 23, 1929. This addition increased the seating capacity to about 15,000. The field was razed in 1988 and was replaced by the soccer field that is presently there.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">5</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>Edgecliff Hall [Formerly Alumni Science Hall]</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1920/1962" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1920-1962</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" 1999" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1999</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains information on: 1. Geoghegan Language Laboratory; 2. Renovation and renaming.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>Completed and opened for classes in September, 1920, it was the first building constructed by St. Xavier College on its new Avondale campus. It was a gift from the alumni who contributed to the Diamond Jubilee Fund of St. Xavier College in 1915. After extensive renovation, it was rededicated in April, 2000, and renamed Edgecliff Hall to honor the former Edgecliff College and its graduates. The original cost of the building was $188,000.00.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">5</container><container type="Folder">4</container><unittitle>Elet Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1927/1988" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1927-1988</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains various materials pertaining to Elet Hall, chiefly regulations for student conduct in this facility.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>Elet Hall is located on Winding Way on the West Campus. It was built as a dormitory which accommodated about 100 students. The formal opening took place on October 4, 1924. With its opening Xavier once again became a "boarding institution." The building was named after Xavier's first Jesuit president, John A. Elet, S.J.. The original cost of the building was $ 249,000.00.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">5</container><container type="Folder">5</container><unittitle>Fenwick Place [also known as Bishop Fenwick Place]</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2009/2011" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2009-2011</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains sundry documents concerning this property. Included are brochures, a ground blessing program, a news release, and other materials.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>This building is named in honor of Bishop Edward Dominic Fenwick, O.P., the first bishop of Cincinnati and founder of the Athenaeum, as Xavier University was originally called. The dining room within this building is named in honor of Father James E. Hoff, the president of Xavier from 1991 to 2000.  The ground blessing took place on May 7, 2010. The building opened in August, 2011. The building is home to student residences and the offices of the Bursar, Registrar, Mission and Identity, among others.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">5</container><container type="Folder">6</container><unittitle>Flynn Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1991 August 14" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1991 August 14</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the dedication program for the Center (dated August 14, 1991).</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>This building was originally named the Lawrence J. Flynn, S.J. Broadcast Center. Its original address was 1648 Herald Avenue, but was changed to 1648 Musketeer Drive. The building was named to honor the Rev. Lawrence J. Flynn, S.J., founder of Xavier radio, and was dedicated on August 14, 1991. The building was originally part of the U.S. Shoe Corporation property which was donated to Xavier in 1978. It was home to the Xavier radio station, WVXU-FM, from approximately 1991 to 2005. Xavier sold WVXU in March, 2005. Sometime after 2005, the Center became an office building housing several Xavier services including the campus police.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">5</container><container type="Folder">7</container><unittitle>Gallagher Student Center</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1998/2002" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1998-2002</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains various brochures and the script of the dedication ceremony of the building.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>The Gallagher Student Center is located at the juncture of the Academic Mall and the Residential Mall, across from Bellarmine Chapel. It is named in honor of Charles P. Gallagher, Class of 1960, the principal donor. The building's original cost was $ 13,955,000.00. The building contains a theatre, bookstore, conference rooms, offices, a food court and shops. It replaced the University Center Building which stood on the same site. It was dedicated and opened in 2002.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">6</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>Hailstones Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1976/1985" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1976-1985</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. Timeline of the building's construction and description of the hall; 2. Correspondence pertaining to the construction of the hall; 3. Groundbreaking Ceremony (November 29, 1979); 4. Dedication of the hall (April 30, 1981); 5. The addition of a third floor to the hall; 6. Photo of the hall.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>Hailstones Hall (formerly called the College of Business Administration Building) was named in honor of Dr. Thomas J. Hailstones, founder and first dean of the College of Business Administration (now known as the Williams College of Business). Groundbreaking took place on November 29, 1979 and the dedication occurred on April 30, 1981. A third floor was added several years later. The original cost of the building was approximately $4,300,000.00.</p><p>In 2010, the Williams College of Business moved to the newly constructed Stephen and Dolores Smith Hall. Then the College of Social Sciences, Education and Health moved into Hailstones Hall.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">6</container><container type="Folder">1A</container><unittitle>Hailstones Hall Correspondence and Programs</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1979/1985" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1979-1985</unitdate></did></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">6</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>Herald Avenue (Closing of)</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1957/1960" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1957-1960</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder consists chiefly of correspondence concerning the closure of Herald Avenue and transfer of the property to Xavier University.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>On May 7, 1958 the City of Cincinnati vacated Herald Avenue from Dana Avenue to Ledgewood Avenue and sold the property to Xavier University. Xavier renamed the street the "Academic Mall."</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">6</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>Hinkle Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1953/1957" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1953-1957</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. Documents pertaining to the two statues on the exterior of the Hall; 2. 1957 prank: Hinkle Hall for sale; 3. Floor plans of the Hall before and after the departure of the Jesuit Community in 1970; 4.Photos of the Hall and O'Brien Terrace.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>Hinkle Hall is located on the Academic Mall between Schmidt Hall and Albers Biology Hall. It was named in honor of Mrs. Frederick Wallis Hinkle, the principal donor. Built at an original cost of $ 256,000.00, it was completed in 1920. It served as the residence of the Jesuit community from 1920 to 1970, after which the Jesuits moved to Schott Hall. It became a faculty office building in 1970.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">6</container><container type="Folder">4</container><unittitle>Hinkle Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1970/1974" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1970-1974</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains materials pertaining to the renovation of the Hall after the Jesuit Community moved its residence to Schott Hall in early February, 1970.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">7</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>Husman Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1963/1990" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1963-1990</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. Correspondence concerning the construction of the Hall; 2. Dedication and blessing of the Hall (November 28, 1965); 3. Floor plans, photos and drawings of the Hall.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>Husman Hall is a student residence hall. It was named in honor of Harry J. Husman, the principal donor. Built at an original cost of $ 793,000.00, it was blessed and dedicated on November 28, 1965.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">7</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>Husman Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1959/1966" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1959-1966</unitdate><origination><corpname>Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Office of the Executive Vice President</corpname></origination></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains documents on the mortgage of Husman Hall. These documents originally came from the files of Fr. Victor B. Nieporte, the Executive Vice President of Xavier University.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">7</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>Husman Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1969/1981" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1969-1981</unitdate><origination><corpname>Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Office of the Executive Vice President</corpname></origination></did><scopecontent><p>Mortgage documents related to Husman Hall. These documents originally came from the files of Fr. Victor B. Nieporte, the Executive Vice President of Xavier University.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">7</container><container type="Folder">4</container><unittitle>Husman Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1964/1966" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1964-1966</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate><origination><corpname>Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Office of the Executive Vice President</corpname></origination></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains mortgage documents related to Husman Hall. These  documents originally came from the files of Fr. Victor B. Nieporte, the  Executive Vice President of Xavier University.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">7</container><container type="Folder">5</container><unittitle>Joseph Building</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1968" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder includes information about the building, correspondence, dedication brochures, and photos.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>The George J. Joseph Building, housing the Center for Human Development, is located on Dana Avenue near Winding Way. It stands on the site of the old Avondale Athletic Club which became the Xavier Union Building when Xavier purchased the property in the early 1900s. The Joseph Building was built at a cost of $ 450,000.00. It was dedicated on December 1, 1968.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">7</container><container type="Folder">6</container><unittitle>Kuhlman Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1967/1968" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1967-1968</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains information on: 1. Naming of Kuhlman Hall; 2. Dedication of Kuhlman Hall;  3. Photos of Kuhlman Hall; 4. Correspondence about the creation of the James F. Griffin, III, Recreation Lounge; 5. Dedication of the James F. Griffin Recreation Lounge.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>Kuhlman Hall was named in honor of George H. and Rose Kuhlman, parents of Leo G., Kuhlman (Class of 1911) and Lawrence B. Kuhlman (Class of 1914). Built at a cost of $ 1,800,000.00, it was dedicated and blessed on December 10, 1967. It accommodated 432 students. The dedication of the James F. Griffin III  Recreation Lounge within Kuhlman Hall occurred on May 5, 1968.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">8</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>Ledgewood Cul-De-Sac Proposal Book 1</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1992/1993" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1992-1993</unitdate><origination><corpname>Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President</corpname></origination></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains correspondence, minutes, blueprints, and other materials relating to the proposed development of Ledgewood Avenue into a cul-de-sac incorporated into part of the Xavier campus. This folder originally came from files of  Xavier University's  Administrative Vice President.</p></scopecontent><accessrestrict><p>This folder may contain some material with restricted access. Please contact the Xavier archives staff.</p></accessrestrict></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">8</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>Ledgewood Cul-De-Sac Proposal Book 1, Supplement 1</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1992/1993" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1992-1993</unitdate><origination><corpname>Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President</corpname></origination></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains materials found in a pocket of Book One's large three-ring binder.  These materials originally came from the files of Xavier University's Administrative Vice President.</p></scopecontent><accessrestrict><p>This folder may contain some material with restricted access. Please contact the archives staff.</p></accessrestrict></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">8</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>Ledgewood Cul-De-Sac Proposal Book 1, Supplement 2</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1992/1993" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1992-1993</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate><origination><corpname>Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President</corpname></origination></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains materials found in a pocket of Book One's large three-ring binder. These materials originally came from the files of Xavier University's Administrative Vice President.</p></scopecontent><accessrestrict><p>This folder may contain some material with restricted access. Please contact the Xavier archives staff.</p></accessrestrict></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">8</container><container type="Folder">4</container><unittitle>Ledgewood Cul-De-Sac Proposal  Book 1, Supplement 3</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1993 August 14" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1993 August 14</unitdate><origination><corpname>Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President</corpname></origination></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains materials found loose within Book One's large three-ring binder. This is a Cincinnati Herald newspaper of August 14, 1993 containing the headline "XU and City Council Close Ledgewood Drive." This folder originally came from files of Xavier University's Administrative Vice President.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">9</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>Ledgewood Cul-De-Sac Proposal Book 2</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1993" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1993</unitdate><origination><corpname>Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President</corpname></origination></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains correspondence, minutes, blueprints, and other  materials relating to the proposed development of Ledgewood Avenue into a  cul-de-sac incorporated into part of the Xavier campus. This folder  originally came from files of Xavier University's Administrative Vice  President.</p></scopecontent><accessrestrict><p>This folder may contain some material with restricted access. Please contact the Xavier archives staff.</p></accessrestrict></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">9</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>Legdewood Cul-De-Sac Proposal Book 2, Supplement 1</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1986" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1986</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" 1993" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1993</unitdate><origination><corpname>Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President</corpname></origination></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains materials found in a pocket of Book Two's large three-ring binder. These materials originally came from the files of Xavier University's Administrative Vice President.</p></scopecontent><accessrestrict><p>This folder may contain some material with restricted access. Please contact the Xavier archives staff.</p></accessrestrict></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">9</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>Ledgewood Cul-De-Sac Proposal  Book 2, Supplement 2</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1993" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1993</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate><origination><corpname>Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President</corpname></origination></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains materials found in a pocket of Book Two's large three-ring binder. These materials originally came from the files of Xavier University's Administrative Vice President.</p></scopecontent><accessrestrict><p>This folder may contain some material with restricted access. Please contact the Xavier archives staff.</p></accessrestrict></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">9</container><container type="Folder">4</container><unittitle>Ledgewood Cul-De-Sac Proposal Book 2, Supplement 3</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1993" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1993</unitdate><origination><corpname>Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President</corpname></origination></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains materials found in a pocket of Book Two's large three-ring binder. These materials originally came from the files of Xavier University's Administrative Vice President.</p></scopecontent><accessrestrict><p>This folder may contain some material with restricted access. Please contact the Xavier archives staff.</p></accessrestrict></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">10</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>Ledgewood Cul-De-Sac Proposal Book 3</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1993/1997" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1993-1997</unitdate><origination><corpname>Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President</corpname></origination></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains correspondence, minutes, blueprints, and other materials relating to the proposed development of Ledgewood Avenue into a cul-de-sac incorporated into part of the Xavier campus. This folder originally came from files of Xavier University's Administrative Vice President.</p></scopecontent><accessrestrict><p>This folder may contain some material with restricted access. Please contact the Xavier archives staff.</p></accessrestrict></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">10</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>Legdewood Cul-De-Sac Proposal Book 3, Supplement 1 Herald Avenue Program</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1958" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1958</unitdate><origination><corpname>Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President</corpname></origination></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains materials found in a pocket of Book Three's large three-ring binder. The materials are apparently photocopies of  information on the closing of Herald Avenue. These materials originally came from the files of Xavier University's Administrative Vice President.</p></scopecontent><accessrestrict><p>This folder may contain some material with restricted access. Please contact the Xavier archives staff.</p></accessrestrict></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">10</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>Proposed Ledgewood Cul-De-Sac Book 3, Supplement 2</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1987" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1987</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" 1993" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1993</unitdate><origination><corpname>Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President</corpname></origination></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains materials found in a pocket of Book Three's large three-ring binder. These materials originally came from the files of Xavier University's Administrative Vice President.</p></scopecontent><accessrestrict><p>This folder may contain material with restricted access. Please contact the Xavier archives staff.</p></accessrestrict></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">10</container><container type="Folder">4</container><unittitle>Proposed Ledgewood Cul-De-Sac Book 3, Supplement3</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1993" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1993</unitdate><origination><corpname>Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President</corpname></origination></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains materials found in a pocket of Book Three's large three-ring binder. These materials originally came from the files of Xavier University's Administrative Vice President.</p></scopecontent><accessrestrict><p>This folder may contain material with restricted access. Please contact the Xavier archives staff.</p></accessrestrict></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">11</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>Ledgewood Lawsuit</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1993/1994" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1993-1994</unitdate><origination><corpname>Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Administrative Vice President</corpname></origination></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains documentation on a lawsuit concerning  Ledgewood Avenue. These materials originally came from the files of Xavier University's Administrative Vice President.</p></scopecontent><accessrestrict><p>This folder may contain some material with restricted access. Please contact the Xavier archives staff.</p></accessrestrict></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">12</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>Lindner Family Physics Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1991 October 30" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1991 October 30</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains brochures from the dedication of the building on October 30, 1991.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>The Lindner Physics Hall is located on the west side of the Academic Mall between Logan Hall and the Gallagher Student Center. It was named in honor the family of Carl H. Lindner, the principal donor. Mr. Lindner was a noted Cincinnati businessman and philanthropist. The hall was dedicated on October 30, 1991. The hall houses the "Foucault Pendulum" and the Xavier Observatory.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">12</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>Logan Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1929/1953" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1929-1953</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. Last Will and Testament of Mr. Thomas J. Logan along with correspondence pertaining to it; 2. Agenda of the Logan Hall Planning Committee.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>Logan Hall is located on the Academic Mall between Albers Biology Hall and the Lindner Family Physics Hall. It was named in honor of Thomas J. Logan, the principal donor. It was built at an original cost of  $ 651,000.00. It opened for classes in September, 1953 and was officially dedicated on May 22,1954.</p><p>On June 4, 1952, the Century Depository Site, located on the plaza in front of the building, was dedicated by Thomas E. Murray, a member of the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission. At the dedication of the building in 1954, a "Century Depository" containing materials of a scientific nature was sealed. An atomic clock will open the depository on May 22, 2053.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">12</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>Logan Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1950/1954" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1950-1954</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains correspondence pertaining to the construction of Logan Hall.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">12</container><container type="Folder">4</container><unittitle>Logan Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1951/1953" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1951-1953</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder has correspondence containing the bids from contractors for the construction of Logan Hall.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">12</container><container type="Folder">5</container><unittitle>Logan Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1946/1954" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1946-1954</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. Contracts for the construction of Logan Hall; 2. Requisitions for the payment of construction work on Logan Hall.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">12</container><container type="Folder">6</container><unittitle>Logan Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1953/1958" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1953-1958</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. Correspondence pertaining to the "Century Depository" located on the plaza outside the entrance to Logan Hall on the University Drive; 2. Correspondence pertaining to the Albert D. Cash Room on the first floor of Logan Hall; 3. Printed announcements about Logan Hall; 4. Drawings, pictures and photos of Logan Hall.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">13</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>Marion Hall and Carriage House</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1964/1976" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1964-1976</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains a history of Marion Hall, some correspondence, photos, and sketches.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>Marion Hall with its Carriage House was located at 992 Marion Avenue. It was built around 1890 by a German carriage maker named Enger. In March, 1943, the Jesuit Community moved out of Hinkle Hall to make room for the 30th College Training Detachment of the U.S. Army Air Corps. Many of the Jesuits moved into Marion Hall where they lived until September, 1944, when the Air Corps program ended and the Jesuits moved back to Hinkle. On October 12, 1943, Xavier purchased Marion Hall while the Jesuits were living there. Marion became a dormitory in 1945. It housed about 60 students. It became an honors (HAB) dormitory in 1958. The Carriage House was located on the grounds of Marion Hall. It was a two-story structure located to the rear left of the mansion. At the end of the 1990-91 academic year, Marion was closed as a residence hall and the university sold the property shortly thereafter.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">13</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>McGrath Health and Wellness Center</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1956/2011" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1956-2011</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains information on the University Health Service and limited correspondence and other materials related to the service itself.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>The University Health Center has had different locations on campus since its inception in 1947. Originally it was found on the ground floor of the Schmidt Memorial Fieldhouse. Subsequently it moved to the Union House. In 1959 it moved to Sycamore House. In 1960 the facility was housed in McGrath Hall, in memory of the late Dr. Edward J. McGrath, a member of  the university medical staff. In 1965 the Health Service moved to Ledgewood Avenue and shortly thereafter moved to the first floor of Kuhlman Hall. Lastly, the Health Center moved to the present location on Cleaney Avenue.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">13</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>O'Connor Sports Center</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1973/1977" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1973-1977</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. Preliminary plans for the Center; 2. Correspondence concerning construction of the Center, 1974-75; 3. Proposals (bids) from architectural firms, 1974.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>The O'Connor Sports Center is located on the west side of the campus near the soccer field and the Schmidt Memorial Fieldhouse. It was named in honor of Paul L. O'Connor, S.J., president of Xavier from 1955 to 1972. The groundbreaking ceremony for the first phase, named "The Ralph and Patricia Corbett Physical Education Building in the O'Connor Sports Center," took place on May 15, 1975. Dedication of the first phase took place on September 29, 1976. Dedication of the second phase took place on April 30, 1977.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">13</container><container type="Folder">4</container><unittitle>O'Connor Sports Center</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1975/1991" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1975-1991</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. Brochure about the Center; 2. Groundbreaking ceremonies for Phase One, the Ralph and Patricia Corbett Physical Education Building (May 15, 1975); 3. Dedication of Phase One, the Ralph and Patricia Corbett Physical Education Building (September 29, 1976); 4. Dedication of Phase Two (April 30, 1977); 5. Brochures and announcements about the Center's activities (1979-1990); 6. Photos and architect's drawing of the Center.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">13</container><container type="Folder">5</container><unittitle>Parking Garage (Proposed)</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1965/1976" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1965-1976</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains limited correspondence and publications related to the question of parking.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>In the 1960s and 1970s there was some discussion of constructing a parking garage on the Xavier campus. None of these proposals were ever acted upon.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">13</container><container type="Folder">6</container><unittitle>Saint Barbara Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2008" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2008</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains limited historical information on St. Barbara Hall.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>Saint Barbara Hall is located at 3904 Winding Way on the west side of the campus. It was purchased by Xavier from the Melcher family in August, 1947. It has been used as the office of the Reserve Officers' Training Corps. (ROTC). St Barbara is the patron saint of armorers, artillerymen and military engineers.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">13</container><container type="Folder">7</container><unittitle>Schmidt Fieldhouse</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1950" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1950</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" 1967-1969" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1967-1969</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains correspondence, notes, sketches and other materials.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>Schmidt Memorial Fieldhouse was erected to the memory of Frederick A. Schmidt and Apolline Tetedoux Schmidt by their son, Walter S. Schmidt, Class of 1905. It was dedicated on March 7, 1928 The original cost of the structure was $ 325,000.00. In 1928, it was the largest college fieldhouse in Ohio.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">13</container><container type="Folder">8</container><unittitle>Schmidt Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1966" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1966</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" 2013" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 2013</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains limited correspondence.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>Schmidt Hall (the Walter Seton Schmidt Library Building) is located between Edgecliff Hall (previously, the Alumni Science Hall) and Hinkle Hall. It was named in honor of Walter Seton Schmidt, Class of 1905, who was the principal donor. The original cost of the structure was $ 260,000.00. It was dedicated in May, 1926. The building originally housed the University Library including the high vaulted Mary G. Lodge Reading Room. It also housed Bellarmine Chapel, classrooms and the seismographic station. Later it housed the University Comptroller's office, the Conaton Board Room, the offices of the university president, the academic vice president (provost) and the financial vice president.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">14</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>Schott Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1962/1970" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1962-1970</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" 1983 May 10" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1983 May 10</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. Program of the Dedication Ceremony (June 27, 1970); 2. Correspondence pertaining to the construction of Schott Hall.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>The Walter E. Schott, Sr., Memorial Building was named in honor of Walter E. Schott, Sr.. The principal donor was the Walter E. Schott Family Foundation. Built as the residence for the Xavier Jesuit Community at a cost of $ 2,200,000.00, the facility was dedicated and blessed on June 27, 1970, by Paul E. Leibold, Archbishop of Cincinnati. In early January, 1991, the Jesuit Community moved out of Schott Hall into the Linkshire Apartment building at 3844 Victory Parkway. Schott then became a faculty office building. Several years later, the Financial Aid Office and the Undergraduate Admission Office moved into the lower floors of the Hall.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">14</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>Schott Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1969/1971" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1969-1971</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains photos, plans and sketches of the Hall.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">14</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>Smith Hall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains a brochure concerning Smith Hall.</p></scopecontent><relatedmaterial><p>See XUA-53, the Xavier University Master Building Plans collection for further information on Smith Hall.</p></relatedmaterial><bioghist><p>Smith Hall was named in honor of Stephen and Dolores Smith. Stephen Smith is a member of the Xavier Class of 1968 and is a member of the Xavier Board of Trustees. This facility is home to Xavier's Williams College of Business Administration. It was dedicated in July, 2010 and opened in August, 2010. It is part of the James E. Hoff, S.J., Academic Quadrangle. With its signature two story atrium, scrolling stock tickers, high-tech classrooms, Wall Street-style trading room and Bloomberg financial database terminals, Smith Hall is state-of-the-art.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">14</container><container type="Folder">4</container><unittitle>Sycamore House</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1949/1954" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1949-1954</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" 1974 October 3" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1974 October 3</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains limited correspondence.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>Built around 1911, Sycamore House was purchased by Xavier University on May 17, 1954. At one time this was the home of Fritz Reiner, the conductor of the Cincinnati Symphony Orchestra. Originally named "the Elet Hall Annex," it served as a student residence adjoining Elet Hall. It later served as the office of the University Health Center. Currently it serves as the office of Psychological Services.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">14</container><container type="Folder">5</container><unittitle>Tibbles Avenue, Closing of</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1964/1965" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1964-1965</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains limited correspondence.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>Sometime in late 1964 or early 1965 the City of Cincinnati vacated Tibbles Avenue between Herald Avenue and Riley Avenue and sold the property to Xavier University. Tibbles Avenue was apparently located just east of where Husman Hall and Kuhlman Hall now stand.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">14</container><container type="Folder">6</container><unittitle>Union House (Red Building)</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1942/1946" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1942-1946</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" 1966" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1966</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder includes articles and correspondence about this facility.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>Union House was located on Dana Avenue near Winding Way. This structure was built as the clubhouse of the Avondale Athletic Club around 1898 and was a landmark in the area. Also known as the "Old Red Building," it served as the university cafeteria and recreation center until the University Center was built in 1965. It was razed in 1966 to make way for the Joseph Building.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">15</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>University Center Building</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1958/2000" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1958-2000</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. Groundbreaking Ceremony (December 12, 1963); 2. Dedication of the Center (October 31, 1965); 3. The Theatre in the University Center; 4. The Musketeer Grill and its mural in the University Center; 5. Food Service in the University Center; 6. Proposal for a rathskeller (bar) in the Center (1973); 7. Relocation of Tucker's Tavern (1976).</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>The University Center Building was located where the Gallagher Student Center now stands. It was built at an original cost of $ 2,250,000.00. Groundbreaking took place on December 12, 1963. The dedication and blessing by Archbishop Alter took place on October 31, 1965. This building contained a cafeteria, theatre, the Musketeer Grill, a bookstore, lounges, a game room, and offices, including that of the university's president. It was razed in the summer of 2000 in order to make room for the Gallagher Student Center.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">15</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>University Center</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1957/1967" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1957-1967</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. Early proposals pertaining to the Center; 2. Papers pertaining to the Federal loan to finance the Center; 3. Brochure about the Center.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">15</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>University Center</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1965" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1965</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder includes floor plans, sketches and photos of the Center.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">15</container><container type="Folder">4</container><unittitle>University Center</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1964/1966" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1964-1966</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains correspondence and records pertaining to the construction and use of the Center, including the minutes of the Committee on Policy for the University Center Building.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">15</container><container type="Folder">5</container><unittitle>Victory Parkway Fields</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1998/2002" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1998-2002</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder includes memorandums, news clippings and diagrams, a draft lease agreement,  along with other materials.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>Victory Parkway Fields are located on Victory Parkway between Ledgewood and Hopkins Avenues in North Avondale. These grounds were dedicated and opened on June 16, 2001. Under an agreement signed by Xavier University and the Cincinnati Park Board and unanimously approved by Cincinnati City Council, the city leased this land to Xavier for $1.00 per year for 98 years. Xavier provided the entire cost of the $ 2,000,000.00 renovation and will maintain the land at no cost to taxpayers. The fields include a soccer field, a baseball diamond, 6 tennis courts and a bike/walking path.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">15</container><container type="Folder">6</container><unittitle>The Villa (Theda Bara House)</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2011" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains limited correspondence and a news clipping.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>The Villa was also called the Theda Bara House and also the Honors House. Xavier acquired the Villa in 1979 from Dr. Joseph Link, professor emeritus of economics, as part of a six-buildings deal which included three apartments (the Linkshire, the University and the Manor House), the Tudor Lodge, the Fraternity House, and the Villa. The Villa was razed in the 2000s. For a history of the Villa and its historical significance, consult the Xavier Magazine, Fall 2001 issue, in which the article entitled "This Old House" appears.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">16</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>Village Student Apartment Complex</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1986/1987" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1986-1987</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. A proposal from Lorenz and Williams, Incorporated; 2. Phase One Report; 3. Schematic Site Design for Phase One Report.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>The Xavier Village Student Apartment Complex is located on the southeast corner of Dana Avenue and Victory Parkway. The groundbreaking ceremony was on September 28, 1988. The dedication ceremony was on September 29, 1989. It opened in the fall of 1989.It comprised 56 apartments of either 2 or 3 or 4 bedrooms each.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">16</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>Village Student Apartment Complex</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1987" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1987</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. Market Survey and Analysis (1987); 2. Design, Development Agreement; Financial Scenarios; 3. Schematic Design of Project; 4. Correspondence.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">16</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>Village Student Apartment Complex</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1988" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1988</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. Planning and construction of the Village (1998); 2. Deed of purchase of the land for the Village (1988).</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">16</container><container type="Folder">4</container><unittitle>Village Student Apartment Complex</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1988" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1988</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. Final Focus Group Report (1988); 2. The minutes and final report of the committee charged with preparing a marketing plan for the Village.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">16</container><container type="Folder">5</container><unittitle>Village Student Apartment Complex</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1988/1991" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1988-1991</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. Groundbreaking ceremony (September 28, 1988); 2. Brochure announcing the opening of the Village; 3. Dedication Ceremony (September 29, 1989); 4. Correspondence, announcements, etc. (1989-1991).</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">16</container><container type="Folder">6</container><unittitle>Walker House</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1969" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1969</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains limited correspondence.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>The Walker House was located at 1500 Dana Avenue on the north side of the street. Xavier University purchased this residential home. On November 23, 1969, the house was dedicated to the memory of Dr. Russell J. Walker, a professor of accounting and former assistant dean of the College of Business Administration. At the time of the dedication the house served as the office of the Institute of Business Services and the Hospital Administration program. Later it was the Financial Aid office. It was razed sometime in the 1990s to make way for the Admission Office parking lot on Dana Avenue outside Schott Hall.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">16</container><container type="Folder">7</container><unittitle>Xavier Commons (Student Residence)</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2000/2001" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2000-2001</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder includes a news release, news clippings and a diagram.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>The Xavier Commons is located on Herald Avenue opposite the Cintas Center. It's original cost was $ 14,000,000.00. It opened in the fall of 2001. It has 71 apartments including one for the president of the University. It is a four story building. About 250 of the approximately 274 residents live in 4 bedroom units. The remainder are in 2 and 3 bedroom apartments. Construction was funded through 30 year tax-exempt bonds issued by the Ohio Higher Education Facilities Commission.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">17</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>Building Inventories</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2000/2006" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2000-2006</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains various inventories of Xavier buildings. Inventories give such information as date of construction, square footage, street addresses, etc..</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">17</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>Property Transactions</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1931/1968" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1931-1968</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains limited correspondence concerning various Xavier property transactions.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">17</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>Donors, Supervisors, Etc.</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1954/1972" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1954-1972</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. List of donors of buildings (1954); 2. Dedication Committees (1965); 3. Lists of building supervisors (1972); 4. Memorials on campus (undated).</p></scopecontent></c01></dsc></archdesc>
</ead>