<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "http://www.library.kent.edu/ead.dtd">
<ead>
<eadheader findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="dublin core" repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601">
<eadid mainagencycode="OCX" url="http://ohiolink.edu/EAD/oha.irk.html" countrycode="us">OCX0012</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>Finding aid for the Xavier University Board of Graduate Studies meeting minutes, and other material</titleproper>
<author>Finding aid prepared by Thomas Kennealy, S.J..</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt><publisher>Xavier University Archives and Special Collections</publisher><address><addressline>Xavier University, McDonald Library</addressline><addressline>3800 Victory Parkway</addressline><addressline>Cincinnati, OH 45207</addressline></address><date type="publication">2017</date></publicationstmt></filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded by Tim McCabe using the OhioLINK EAD Application in <date>2013</date></creation>
<langusage>English</langusage>
<descrules>Describing Archives: A Content Standard</descrules>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<archdesc level="collection" type="inventory" relatedencoding="MARC">
<did>
<head>Overview of the Collection</head>
<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
<corpname>Xavier University Archives and Special Collections</corpname>
<address><addressline>Phone: 513-745-4821</addressline>
<addressline>http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives</addressline>
</address>
</repository>
<origination label="Creator:"><corpname encodinganalog="110">Xavier University. Board of Graduate Studies</corpname></origination>
<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Xavier University Board of Graduate Studies meeting minutes, and other material</unittitle>
<physdesc label="Extent:" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>1 linear feet (2 boxes)</extent></physdesc>
<abstract label="Abstract:" encodinganalog="520$a">Meeting minutes and related documents of the Xavier University Board of Graduate Studies.</abstract>
<unitid encodinganalog="035" label="Collection Code" countrycode="us" repositorycode="OCX">XUA- 12</unitid>
<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language:">The records are in <language langcode="eng">English</language></langmaterial>
<physloc label="Location:">Xavier University Archives, Cincinati, Ohio</physloc><unitdate type="inclusive" label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f" normal="1945/2011" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1945-2011</unitdate></did>
<!-- TOP LEVEL METADATA GOES HERE: -->
<bioghist encodinganalog="545"><head>History of Xavier University Board of Graduate Studies</head><p>The Board of Graduate Studies (BOGS) was known formerly as the Graduate Council. The Graduate Council's first meeting was on October 23, 1945. This committee is still in existence under it's present name.</p><bioghist><p>After the initial meeting of the Graduate Council in October, 1945 the Graduate Division, as the Graduate School was initially called, began its existence in the first summer session, June, 1946. In the 1992-93 academic year the name was changed from the Graduate Council to the Board of Graduate Studies. The Board of Graduate Studies (BOGS) is still in existence. In 1971-72 the charge was: "The Council, of which the Dean of the Graduate School is chairman, makes its recommendations to the Academic Vice President on all matters concerning policy and programs in the Graduate School. It is constituted by the chairmen of departments offering graduate programs." In the 1982-83 academic year the charge was: "The Graduate Council consists of the Dean of the Graduate School, ex officio chairperson, the Dean of the College of Business Administration, nine faculty members nominated by the Faculty Committee, and other members of the administration as nominated by the Academic Vice President. The Council makes its recommendation to the Academic Vice President." (Source: the Annual Lists of University Committees).The Annual Document of University Committees  for 2012-2013 provides the following description of the Board of  Graduate Studies: its role, composition, and reporting responsibilities:   "BOARD OF GRADUATE STUDIES   Charge: The Board of Graduate Studies: 1.  Works towards resolving redundancies across colleges involving: new  graduate courses or revisions to existing graduate courses that are  approved by the college curriculum committees; new graduate programs  or revisions to existing graduate programs that are approved by the  college curriculum committees. (Graduate programs are defined in the  University Catalog.) 2. Ensures that resources exist to accommodate the  requirements of new graduate courses and programs or revisions to  existing graduate courses and programs when the requirements draw upon  resources in other colleges. 3. Makes certain that graduate courses or  programs support the Mission of the University. 4. Implements and  decides upon revisions to the graduate University Grading Policies, such  as university grading designations and standards for graduation. 5.  Initiates revisions and recommends improvements to the Graduate  University Catalog. 6. Reviews and makes recommendations on issues  concerning the scheduling of the Graduate Academic Calendar. Membership:  Membership consists of six (6) tenured or tenure-track faculty members  (two from each college elected by the Faculty Assembly), the deans (or  their representatives) of the three colleges, one (1) graduate student  recommended by the Provost and Chief Academic Officer, the University  Registrar (ex officio, non-voting), and the Provost and Chief Academic  Officer (ex officio, non-voting). The Chair will be elected from the  faculty members by the committee. Voting: Approval of a proposal  requires a quorum and a simple majority vote of affirmation from those  in attendance. Reporting: The Board of Graduate Studies reports to the  Provost and Chief Academic Officer and to the Faculty Committee through  an appointed liaison. Also, the Board of Graduate Studies has the  responsibility to respond to the Curriculum and/or Program Committees  that have submitted graduate course or program descriptions for review  as described above in the charge section."</p></bioghist></bioghist><scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a"><head>Scope and Content</head><p>Meeting minutes and related content from the Xavier University Board of Graduate Studies. Not every academic year is represented in this paper copy collection.</p><scopecontent/></scopecontent><arrangement encodinganalog="351$b"><head>Statement of Arrangement</head><p>The collection is arranged into folders chronologically.</p></arrangement><separatedmaterial encodinganalog="544 0"><head>Separated Material</head><p>Digital copies of the Board of Graduate Studies meeting minutes are also found in the Xavier University Archive's permanent storage drive. Holdings begin with December 1, 2004 and continue to the present. There are some gaps in the digital holdings. For further information, contact the Xavier University Archives staff.</p></separatedmaterial><accessrestrict encodinganalog="506"><head>Restrictions on Access</head><p>Access restricted. Please contact the Xavier University Archives staff.</p></accessrestrict><prefercite encodinganalog="524"><head>Preferred Citation</head><p>Box Number, Folder Number, XUA-12, Xavier University Board of Graduate Studies meeting minutes and other material, Special Collections and Archives, Xavier University Library, Cincinnati, Ohio.</p></prefercite><accruals encodinganalog="584"><head>Accruals</head><p>There may be additions to this collection in the future.</p></accruals><controlaccess><head>Indexing Terms</head><p>The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.</p><controlaccess><head>Subjects:</head><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Universities and colleges-Ohio-Graduate work</subject></controlaccess><controlaccess><head>Organizations/Corporations:</head><corpname encodinganalog="610$a" source="lcsh">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)-- Curricula</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Graduate Council</corpname></controlaccess></controlaccess><dsc type="combined"><head>Detailed Description of The Collection</head><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><unittitle>Board of Graduate Studies Meeting Minutes</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1945/1995" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1945-1995</unitdate></did></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><unittitle>Board of Graduate Studies Meeting Minutes</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1995/2011" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1995-2011</unitdate></did></c01></dsc></archdesc>
</ead>