<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "http://www.library.kent.edu/ead.dtd">
<ead>
<eadheader findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="dublin core" repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601">
<eadid mainagencycode="OCX" url="http://ohiolink.edu/EAD/oha.irk.html" countrycode="us">OCX0091</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>John B. Hart Conference on the Foundations of Quantum Mechanics Collection</titleproper>
<author>Thomas Kennealy, SJ</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt><publisher>Xavier University Archives and Special Collections</publisher><address><addressline>Xavier University, McDonald Library</addressline><addressline>1535 Musketeer Drive</addressline><addressline>Cincinnati, OH 45207-3341</addressline></address><date type="publication">2018</date></publicationstmt></filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded by Anne Ryckbost using the OhioLINK EAD Creation Tool in <date>2017</date></creation>
<langusage>English</langusage>
<descrules>Describing Archives: A Content Standard</descrules>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<archdesc level="collection" type="inventory" relatedencoding="MARC">
<did>
<head>Overview of the Collection</head>
<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
<corpname>Xavier University Archives and Special Collections</corpname>
<address><addressline>Phone: 513-745-4821</addressline>
<addressline>http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives</addressline>
</address>
</repository>
<origination label="Creator:"><persname encodinganalog="100">Hart, John B., 1924-2007</persname></origination>
<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">John B. Hart Conference on the Foundations of Quantum Mechanics Collection</unittitle>
<physdesc label="Extent:" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>2.5 linear feet (6 manuscript boxes and 10.16 GB)</extent></physdesc>
<abstract label="Abstract:" encodinganalog="520$a">Collection documents the Conference on the Foundations of Quantum Mechanics, which the Xavier University Department of Physics hosted from October 1-5, 1962. The conference, jointly sponsored by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration, the Office of Naval Research, and the Judge Robert S. Marx Foundation, was chaired by physics professor Boris Podolsky. John B. Hart served as conference manager. The principal participants were six eminent physicists, including two Nobel Prize winners, who were joined by sixteen other specially invited physicists from around the world. The collection contains conference planning documentation, grant materials, financial records, correspondence, reports, publicity, and photographs. It includes sound recordings of public lectures and transcripts of the conference proceedings. The collection also includes a small amount of papers and lectures on other physics-related topics.</abstract>
<unitid encodinganalog="035" label="Collection Code" countrycode="us" repositorycode="OCX">XUA-90</unitid>
<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language:">The records are in <language langcode="eng">English</language></langmaterial>
<physloc label="Location:">Xavier University Archives, Cincinnati, Ohio</physloc><unitdate type="inclusive" label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f" normal="1961/2005" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1961-2005</unitdate><unitdate type="bulk" label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$g" normal="1961/1964" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1961-1964</unitdate></did>
<!-- TOP LEVEL METADATA GOES HERE: -->
<bioghist encodinganalog="545"><head>Biography of John B. Hart and History of the Conference on the Foundations of Quantum Mechanics</head><p>John B. Hart (1924-2007) was a professor in the physics department at Xavier University from 1951-1999. Prior to that, he was a graduate assistant and assistant instructor in the department. Hart often chaired the department from 1957-1971 and served as chair again in 1982-1983. Hart was an officer in the United States Navy in World War II and then continued with the United States Navy Reserves for twenty-six years. He earned his bachelor's degree (1944) and master's degree (1950) from Xavier University.</p><p>One of Hart's notable accomplishments was being the conference manager for the Conference on the Foundations of Quantum Mechanics held at Xavier University in October 1962. Boris Podolsky served as conference chair and Frederick Werner as the assistant chair. The conference was the idea of Podolsky, who had been an associate of Albert Einstein at Princeton University and had joined the Xavier physics department in 1961 after teaching at the University of Cincinnati. The purpose of the conference was to examine some of the fundamental issues in the foundations of quantum mechanics, including the Einstein-Podolsky-Rosen Effect, the quantum measurement problem, and to what extent had relative theory and quantum theory been united consistently. The conference had six main participants, two of whom were Nobel Prize winners (P. A. M. Dirac and Eugene Wigner), plus a limited-attendance group of sixteen physicists who met in private sessions. Some conference events on the first two days were open to the general public. Hart also participated in the 40th anniversary commemoration of the conference in 2002.</p><bioghist><p>Not specified</p></bioghist></bioghist><scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a"><head>Scope and Content</head><p>This collection documents the Conference on  the Foundations of Quantum Mechanics, which the Xavier University Department of Physics hosted from October 1 to 5 in 1962. Materials include conference planning documentation, correspondence,  publicity, and photographs. The collection contains sound recordings of public lectures and transcripts of the conference proceedings. In addition, there is also a small amount of papers and lectures on other physics-related topics.</p><scopecontent><p>Series I, Conference on the Foundations of Quantum Mechanics, 1961-2003, contains conference proposals, grant materials, financial records, correspondence, invitations, registrations, event schedules, publicity, and photographs. Included is a photograph album documenting conference events, most of which took place in Alter Hall or Logan Hall on the campus of Xavier University. There were six main participants: Boris Podolsky, Xavier University; P. A. M. Dirac, Cambridge University (England); Nathan Rosen, Technion (Haifa, Israel), W. H. Furry, Harvard University; Eugene Wigner, Princeton University; and Yakir Aharonov, Yeshiva University. The series contains correspondence from these six and the sixteen other participants including Eugene Merzbacher, William Band, Oldwig von Roos,  Solomon Schwebel, Abner Shimony, and Kaiser Kunz. The series also contains sound recordings of public lectures by Dirac, Furry, Wignar, and Aharonov and transcripts of the conference proceedings. While the conference proceedings were not formally published, Dirac's lecture, "The Evolution of the Physicist's Picture of Nature," delivered on the second evening of the conference, was published in <title render="italic">Scientific American </title>(May 1963). Frederick Werner published a summary of the conference in <title render="italic">Physics Today</title> (January 1964).  Both articles are in the collection.</p><p>Series II, Physics Publications and Lecture, 1964-2005, contains CDs of a sound recording of a lecture titled, "Projective Geometry: Origin of Quantum Equations" given by Dirac at Boston University on October 30, 1972. The series also includes two papers by Solomon Schwebel that were sent to John B. Hart in 1964.</p></scopecontent></scopecontent><arrangement encodinganalog="351$b"><head>Statement of Arrangement</head><p>This collection is arranged into two series: Series I: Conference on the Foundations of Quantum Mechanics and Series II: Physics Publications and Lectures.</p></arrangement><relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544 1"><head>Related Material</head><p>XUA-66, Xavier University Department of Physics records, Xavier University Archives, Xavier University, Cincinnati, Ohio</p></relatedmaterial><processinfo encodinganalog="583"><head>Processing Information</head><p>Reel-to-reel tapes of conference lectures were converted to digital files in 2016. Multiple tracks of individual lectures were combined during this process. CD contents were migrated to University Archives electronic storage in 2017.</p></processinfo><accessrestrict encodinganalog="506"><head>Restrictions on Access</head><p>This collection is open for research. Due to preservation concerns, original audio reel-to-reel tapes and CDs cannot be used. Contact archives staff for access to digital access copies.</p></accessrestrict><userestrict encodinganalog="540"><head>Restrictions on Use</head><p>This collection is the physical property of Xavier University. Copyright law of the United States governs the reproduction of copyrighted material. The User assumes full responsibility for the fair use of materials requested in total compliance with the copyright law of the United States that may arise through the use of any requested materials.</p></userestrict><prefercite encodinganalog="524"><head>Preferred Citation</head><p>Identification of item, Box Number, Folder Number, XUA-90, John B. Hart Conference on the Foundations of Quantum Mechanics Collection, Special Collections and University Archives, Xavier University Library, Cincinnati, Ohio.</p></prefercite><acqinfo encodinganalog="541"><head>Acquisition Information</head><p>Donated by Verna Gibson Hart, 2014 (XUA2016-02)</p></acqinfo><bibliography><head>Publication note</head><p>Conference lecture and summary published in:</p><bibref>Dirac, P. A. M.  "The Evolution of the Physicist's Picture of Nature." <title render="italic">Scientific American</title>, May 1963.</bibref><bibref>Werner, Frederick. "The Foundations of Quantum Mechanics: A Conference Report." <title render="italic">Physics Today</title>, January 1964.</bibref></bibliography><controlaccess><head>Indexing Terms</head><p>The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.</p><controlaccess><head>Subjects:</head><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Quantum theory.</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Quantum theory--History.</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Physics--Study and teaching.</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Physics--Research.</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Einstein-Podolsky-Rosen experiment</subject></controlaccess><controlaccess><head>Persons:</head><persname encodinganalog="100$a" source="local">Hart, John B., 1924-2007</persname><persname encodinganalog="100$a" source="lcnaf">Podolsky, Boris, 1896-1966</persname><persname encodinganalog="100$a" source="lcnaf">Dirac, P. A. M. (Paul Adrien Maurice), 1902-1984</persname><persname encodinganalog="100$a" source="local">Werner, Frederick</persname><persname encodinganalog="100$a" source="lcnaf">Rosen, Nathan, -1995</persname><persname encodinganalog="100$a" source="lcnaf">Wigner, Eugene Paul, 1902-1995</persname><persname encodinganalog="100$a" source="lcnaf">Aharonov, Yakir, 1932-</persname><persname encodinganalog="100$a" source="lcnaf">Furry, W. H. (Wendell Hinkle), 1907-1984</persname><persname encodinganalog="100$a" source="local">Schwebel, Solomon L.</persname></controlaccess><controlaccess><head>Organizations/Corporations:</head><corpname encodinganalog="110$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Department of Physics.</corpname></controlaccess><controlaccess><head>Material Types:</head><genreform encodinganalog="655$a" source="lcgft">Live sound recordings</genreform><genreform encodinganalog="655$a" source="gmgpc">Photographic prints</genreform></controlaccess></controlaccess><dsc type="combined"><head>Detailed Description of The Collection</head><c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Series I, Conference on the Foundations of Quantum Mechanics</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1961/2003" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1961-2003</unitdate></did><c02 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">1-2</container><unittitle>Conference proposal</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1961/1962" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1961-1962</unitdate></did></c02><c02 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">3-6</container><unittitle>Grant materials</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1962/1963" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1962-1963</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>Contains grant award letters, incoming and outgoing correspondence, financial records, and reports for the National Aeronautics and Space Administration grant, the Office of Naval Research grant, and the award from the Judge Robert S. Marx Foundation. Financial records include budgets, receipts, and expenses.</p></scopecontent></c02><c02 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">7-16</container><unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1961/1966" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1961-1966</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>Contains correspondence from conference organizers and invited guests, including such notable physicists as Niels Bohr, Alfred Lande, P. A. M. Dirac, Eugene Wigner, and Louis de Broglie. Bohr, Lande, and de Broglie declined the invitation. Correspondence discusses such topics as conference funding, travel arrangements, admission tickets, special events, lecture arrangements, and requests for recordings, transcripts, and publications of conference proceedings. The majority of the correspondence is either written by or directed to Hart as conference manager or Podolsky as chair.</p></scopecontent></c02><c02 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">17</container><unittitle>List of principal participants and biographical information</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1962" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1962</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>Includes a photocopy of a letter of recommendation written by Albert Einstein to the University of Cincinnati on behalf of Boris Podolsky.</p></scopecontent></c02><c02 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">18</container><unittitle>Registration forms</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1962" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1962</unitdate></did></c02><c02 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">19</container><unittitle>Schedule of events and handouts for participants</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1962" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1962</unitdate></did></c02><c02 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">1-2</container><unittitle>Special events</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1962" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1962</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>Contains invitations, tickets, and guest lists for special events hosted during the conference.</p></scopecontent></c02><c02 level="file"><did><container type="Box">6</container><unittitle>Sound recordings of lectures</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1962 October" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1962 October</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>Recordings consist of public lectures given by Aharonov, Furry, and Wigner on the first day of the conference, and by Dirac on the second day.</p></scopecontent><altformavail><p>Reel-to-reel tapes have been digitized. Access is available in Exhibit, the digital repository of Xavier University Library.</p></altformavail><c03 level="item"><did><container type="Reel">XUA90-a01</container><unittitle>On the Significance of Electromagnetic Potentials in the Quantum Domain</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1962 October 1" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1962 October 1</unitdate><origination><persname>Aharonov, Yakir, 1932-</persname></origination></did></c03><c03 level="item"><did><container type="Reel">XUA90-a02-01</container><container type="Reel">XUA90-a02-02</container><unittitle>The Quantum-Mechanical Description of States and Measurements</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1962 October 1" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1962 October 1</unitdate><origination><persname>Furry, W. H. (Wendell Hinkle), 1907-1984</persname></origination></did><altformavail><p>Lecture is transcribed in the conference transcript available online in Exhibit, the digital repository of Xavier University Library.</p></altformavail></c03><c03 level="item"><did><container type="Reel">XUA90-a02-02</container><container type="Reel">XUA90-a03</container><unittitle>Concept of Observation in Quantum Mechanics</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1962 October 1" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1962 October 1</unitdate><origination><persname>Wigner, Eugene Paul, 1902-1995</persname></origination></did><altformavail><p>Lecture is transcribed in the conference transcript available online in Exhibit, the digital repository of Xavier University Library.</p></altformavail></c03><c03 level="item"><did><container type="Reel">XUA90-a04-01</container><container type="Reel">XUA90-a04-02</container><unittitle>The Evolution of the Physicist's Picture of Nature</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1962 October 2" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1962 October 2</unitdate><origination><persname>Dirac, P. A. M. (Paul Adrien Maurice), 1902-1984</persname></origination></did><altformavail><p>Lecture is transcribed in the conference transcript available in Exhibit, the digital repository of Xavier University Library.</p></altformavail></c03></c02><c02 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">3-13</container><unittitle>First draft of conference transcript</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1962" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1962</unitdate></did></c02><c02 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">14</container><unittitle>Distribution lists for conference transcript</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1964" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1964</unitdate></did></c02><c02 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">15-16</container><unittitle>Transcript corrections from conference participants</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1964" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1964</unitdate></did></c02><c02 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Piece">1</container><container type="Box">3-4</container><container type="Box">5</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>Conference manuscript</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1962" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1962</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" 2002" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 2002</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>A transcript of the conference proceedings was created by Frederick Werner from sound recordings of the conference. The recordings used for the transcript are not all represented in the collection. Not everything was transcribed: material previously published, including presentations by Jack Rivers, Solomon Schwebel, and Eugene Guth, was omitted. The transcript includes portions of both the public and closed sessions. Included in the series are copies of the conference manuscript for W. H. Furry, Nathan Rosen, Eugene Merzbacher, and John B. Hart along with corrected and uncorrected drafts in print typescript and on CDs.</p></scopecontent><altformavail><p>Conference manuscript has been digitized and is available in Exhibit, the digital repository of the Xavier University Library. Digital copies of transcript drafts on CDs exist. Contact archives staff for access.</p></altformavail></c02><c02 level="file"><did><container type="Box">5</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>Photograph album of conference activities</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1962" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1962</unitdate></did></c02><c02 level="file"><did><container type="Box">5</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>Photographs of participants</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1962" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1962</unitdate></did></c02><c02 level="file"><did><container type="Box">5</container><container type="Folder">4</container><unittitle>Public relations policy</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1962" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1962</unitdate></did></c02><c02 level="file"><did><container type="Box">5</container><container type="Folder">5-6</container><unittitle>Publicity</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1962/1994" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1962-1994</unitdate></did></c02><c02 level="file"><did><container type="Box">5</container><container type="Folder">7</container><unittitle>"The Evolution of the Physicist's Picture of Nature," <title render="italic">Scientific American</title></unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1963 May" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1963 May</unitdate></did></c02><c02 level="file"><did><container type="Box">5</container><container type="Folder">8</container><unittitle>Pamphlets on publishing articles</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1963/1964" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1963-1964</unitdate></did></c02><c02 level="file"><did><container type="Box">5</container><container type="Folder">9</container><unittitle>40th anniversary commemoration of the Conference on the Foundations of Quantum Mechanics materials</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1992/2004" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1992-2004</unitdate><origination><corpname>Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)</corpname></origination></did><scopecontent><p>Contains 2 CDs of the transcript, which were digitized and converted to Portable Document Format by Joseph Brinkman in 2002. Brinkman corrected most insignificant spelling and grammatical errors but retained an emphasis on recreating the original document, including handwritten notes by the attendees and certain grammatical styles. Transcript includes articles published by Dirac and Werner as well as an introduction written by Hart in 2002.</p></scopecontent><altformavail><p>Electronic copies of CDs exist. Contact archives staff for access.</p></altformavail></c02></c01><c01 level="series"><did><unittitle>Series II, Physics publications and lectures</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1964/1987" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1964-1987</unitdate></did><arrangement><p>Series is arranged alphabetically by last name of author.</p></arrangement><c02 level="file"><did><container type="Box">5</container><container type="Folder">10</container><unittitle>P. A. M. Dirac, Projective geometry: origin of quantum equations lecture</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1972" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1972</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" 2005" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 2005</unitdate><origination><persname>Dirac, P. A. M. (Paul Adrien Maurice), 1902-1984</persname></origination></did><scopecontent><p>Contains CDs of a sound recording made by Hart of Dirac speaking about projective geometry on October 30, 1972 at Boston University. This recording, according to Hart, includes the personal announcement by Dirac that he had never published his "secret" use of projective geometry in creating quantum mechanics. Roger Penrose offers concluding remarks at the end of the recording.</p></scopecontent><altformavail><p>Electronic copies of CDs exist. Contact archives staff for access.</p></altformavail></c02><c02 level="file"><did><container type="Box">5</container><container type="Folder">11</container><unittitle>Heinz Pagels, Bell's Inequality</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1987" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1987</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>Chapter published in <title render="italic">The World of Physics: A Small Library of the Literature of Physics from Antiquity to the Present</title>, volume 2, edited by Jefferson Hane Weaver. New York: Simon and Schuster, 1987.</p></scopecontent></c02><c02 level="file"><did><container type="Box">5</container><container type="Folder">12</container><unittitle>Solomon Schwebel papers</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1964" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1964</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>Includes physics papers written by Schwebel that he sent to Hart in 1964.</p></scopecontent></c02></c01></dsc></archdesc>
</ead>