<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "http://www.library.kent.edu/ead.dtd">
<ead>
<eadheader findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="dublin core" repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601">
<eadid mainagencycode="OCX" url="http://ohiolink.edu/EAD/oha.irk.html" countrycode="us">OCX0055</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>Xavier University Shrines, Statues and Monuments collection</titleproper>
<author>Thomas P. Kennealy, S.J.</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt><publisher>Xavier University Archives and Special Collections</publisher><address><addressline>Xavier University, McDonald Library</addressline><addressline>1535 Musketeer Drive</addressline><addressline>Cincinnati, OH 45207-3341</addressline></address><date type="publication">2018</date></publicationstmt></filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded by Tim McCabe using the OhioLINK EAD Application in <date>2015</date></creation>
<langusage>English</langusage>
<descrules>Describing Archives: a Content Standard</descrules>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<archdesc level="collection" type="inventory" relatedencoding="MARC">
<did>
<head>Overview of the Collection</head>
<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
<corpname>Xavier University Archives and Special Collections</corpname>
<address><addressline>Phone: 513-745-4821</addressline>
<addressline>http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives</addressline>
</address>
</repository>
<origination label="Creator:"><corpname encodinganalog="110">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)</corpname></origination>
<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Xavier University Shrines, Statues and Monuments collection</unittitle>
<physdesc label="Extent:" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>.25 linear feet (1 box)</extent></physdesc>
<abstract label="Abstract:" encodinganalog="520$a">This collection consists of correspondence, documentation, brochures, descriptions, photos, diagrams and other materials concerning  the  shrines, statues, monuments, fountains and permanent plaques on the Xavier University campus. It is not complete.</abstract>
<unitid encodinganalog="035" label="Collection Code" countrycode="us" repositorycode="OCX">XUA-55</unitid>
<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language:">The records are in <language langcode="eng">English</language></langmaterial>
<physloc label="Location:">Xavier University Archives, Cincinnati, Ohio</physloc><unitdate type="inclusive" label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f" normal="1912/2014" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912-2014</unitdate></did>
<!-- TOP LEVEL METADATA GOES HERE: -->
<scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a"><head>Scope and Content</head><p>This is a small collection of information on certain art works, shrines, etc. found on the campus of Xavier University.</p><scopecontent><p>Not specified</p></scopecontent></scopecontent><arrangement encodinganalog="351$b"><head>Statement of Arrangement</head><p>Arrangement  of information is done by folder alphabetically according to the name of the piece described.</p></arrangement><prefercite encodinganalog="524"><head>Preferred Citation</head><p>Box Number, Folder Number, XUA-55, Shrines, Statues, and Monuments collection, Special Collections and University Archives, Xavier University Library, Cincinnati, Ohio.</p></prefercite><accruals encodinganalog="584"><head>Accruals</head><p>Additions to the collection are expected.</p></accruals><controlaccess><head>Indexing Terms</head><p>The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.</p><controlaccess><head>Subjects:</head><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">World War, 1914-1918--Monuments-- Ohio</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Art in universities and colleges--Ohio</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcnaf">War memorials--Ohio</subject></controlaccess><controlaccess><head>Persons:</head><persname encodinganalog="600$a" source="lcsh">Artagnan, Charles de Batz-Castelmore, comte d', 1613?-1673-- Statues</persname><persname encodinganalog="600$a" source="lcsh">Francis Xavier, Saint, 1506-1552-- Statues</persname><persname encodinganalog="600$a" source="lcsh">Mary, Blessed Virgin, Saint -- Statues</persname></controlaccess><controlaccess><head>Organizations/Corporations:</head><corpname encodinganalog="610$a" source="lcsh">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)</corpname></controlaccess></controlaccess><dsc type="combined"><head>Detailed Description of The Collection</head><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>Budde Fountain</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1912/1927" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1912-1927</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>The George W. Budde Memorial Fountain was named in honor of George W. Budde, Xavier graduate and marine, who was killed in action on November 11, 1918. Budde was killed on the same day of the signing of the Armistice ending the First World War. He is thought to be the last person to die in the war. The  fountain is located on the first floor of Edgecliff Hall (the former Alumni Science Building). It was erected by the American Legion and dedicated on November 2, 1927. The fountain is made of Rookwood pottery.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>Carillon Chimes</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1947/1949" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1947-1949</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>The Carrilon Chimes were proposed by the Xavier Alumni Association in 1948 and were first played at Xavier University at the homecoming game in November, 1948. The total cost of the chimes was $5,500.00. The use of the chimes was discontinued during the 1960s.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>Dance of Tears Statue, Plaza, and Library Courtyard</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1999" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1999</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>The Dance of Tears statue was placed in the courtyard behind the McDonald Library sometime in 1998 or 1999. The sculptor was Barbara Trauth. The sculpture sends a strong pro-life message.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">4</container><unittitle>Fountain between Logan and Albers Halls</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2014" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2014</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains a brief note written by Xavier Archives staff on the origins of this fountain.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>The fountain between Logan and Albers Halls was built by Universal Contracting. It was constructed as part of the formal renovation of the Academic Mall in 1998. It was designed by MSP Architects. The office of the archives has no record of a donor or of a dedication ceremony.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">5</container><unittitle>Landscaping on the Academic and Residential Malls</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1999" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1999</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder has a list of the plants which adorned the Academic Mall and the Residential Mall in 1999.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">6</container><unittitle>Plaque Proclaiming Xavier a Catholic Historical Site</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2001" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</unitdate></did><bioghist><p>At a dedication ceremony held on July 21, 2001, this plaque was presented to Xavier University by the International Order of Alhambra in conjunction with its 49th biennial convention. As of July, 2014 the plaque was attached to the wall of the lobby of the first floor Schmidt Hall .</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">7</container><unittitle>Quo Vadis Monument</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2001" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2001</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This  folder contains several descriptions of the monument and diagrams.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>Quo Vadis is an 18-foot-tall, interactive, stainless steel monument which presently stands on the Residential Mall of the Xavier University campus. It is found between Kuhlman and Brackman Halls. It was erected in 2001 to celebrate the inauguration of Michael J. Graham, S.J. as president.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">8</container><unittitle>Shrine of Our Lady, Queen of Victory and Peace</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1943/2011" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1943-2011</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. Correspondence about the construction of the Shrine; Dedication Ceremony (July 11, 1943); list of donors to the Shrine Fund; 2. May Day Celebration at the Shrine (May 1, 1949); 3. Papers pertaining the history of the Shrine; 4. Re-dedication of the Shrine (November 11, 2011).</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>The Shrine of Our Lady, Queen of Victory and Peace, was erected in 1943 and dedicated that same year. The shrine honors those who have served in the armed forces, especially those who have given their lives. The shrine was presented to the university by Xavier's alumni. The shrine was designed by Albert V. Walters. The shrine's Madonna statue was created from Bedford limestone by the Cincinnati sculptor Ernest Bruce Haswell. Shortly after the Second World War a plaque was affixed to the Shrine identifying the one Xavier graduate killed in the First World War and the 75 who died in the Second World War. Additional names have been added subsequently.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">9</container><unittitle>Statue of D'Artagnan on the Musketeer Plaza of the Academic Mall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1962/1968" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1962-1968</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains correspondence about the creation of the statue and information on the dedication ceremony and dinner of November 2, 1968.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>This sculpture stood on the Academic Mall opposite the main entrance to Alter Hall in a space named the Musketeer Plaza. In the 1990s the statue was removed and placed in storage in the Alumni Center, and the Musketeer Plaza was eliminated as part of the renovation of the Academic Mall. A new statue of D'Artagnan was erected at the entrance to the Cintas Center in 2000. D'artagnan, a 17th Century French Musketeer, is the mascot of Xavier's athletic teams.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">10</container><unittitle>Statue of D'Artagnan on the Musketeer Plaza of the Academic Mall</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1968" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains: 1. History of the statue; 2. History of the use of  the names "Musketeers" and "Legion of Honor;" 3. Dedication ceremony committee; 4. "L'Ordre des Mousquetaires de Xavier University;" 5. Drawings and photos of the statue and plaza.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">11</container><unittitle>Statue of D'Artagnam, The Musketeer, on the Cintas Center Plaza</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains a brief news clipping.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>This statue was erected in 2000 when the Cintas Center opened. Tom Tsuchiya was the creator of this larger than life sculpture of Xavier's mascot, the 17th Century French Musketeer D'Artagnan. D'Artagnan was the hero of Alexandre Dumas' novel "The Three Musketeers." Roland and Mary Moores contributed to the creation of this statue.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">12</container><unittitle>Statue of the Rev. James E. Hoff, S.J., with Two Students</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2002" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2002</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains a university news release on the placement of the statue.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>This statue honors the memory of  the Rev. James E. Hoff, S.J., president of Xavier University from 1991 to 2000 and Chancellor of the university from 2000to 2004. It was created by Tom Tsuchiya. The statue presently stands outside the entrance of the Fenwick Place dining room.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">13</container><unittitle>Statue of Mother Teresa of Calcutta</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains some notes about the statue.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>The statue of Mother Teresa of Calcutta stands outside the east entrance to Smith Hall, the home of the Williams College of Business Administration. It was cast in bronze in Italy. It was donated to Xavier by Bernie Downey and was placed in its present location in  2011.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">14</container><unittitle>Statue of Francis Xavier on the O'Brien Terrace</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1954/1985" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1954-1985</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains some information on both St. Francis Xavier statues.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>The present statue of St. Francis Xavier which stands on the O'Brien Terrace facing Victory Parkway was dedicated in 1985. It was created by Dr. Bernard L. Schmidt, a Xavier faculty member and chair of the Department of Art at the time. It was a gift from the class of 1934 on the 50th anniversary of their graduation. It replaced an earlier statue of St. Francis Xavier dedicated in 1954.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">15</container><unittitle>Statue of Francis Xavier on the Francis Xavier Way Roundabout</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2011" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">2011</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This  folder contains an article about the statue as found in Xavier Magazine (Summer, 2011) and a news article about the statue from Xavier News &amp; Events (11/30/2011).</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>The statue was dedicated and blessed on December 2, 2011.</p></bioghist></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">16</container><unittitle>Wall Crosses in the Cintas Center</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This  folder contains a brochure about the crosses.</p></scopecontent><bioghist><p>Designed by David Camele, these crosses were placed in the campus classrooms sometime around 2000. They were also displayed in an exhibition in the Schiff Family Conference Center in the Cintas Center.. The exhibition was removed from the Cintas Center in the early 2010s.</p></bioghist></c01></dsc></archdesc>
</ead>