<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "http://www.library.kent.edu/ead.dtd">
<ead>
<eadheader findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="dublin core" repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601">
<eadid mainagencycode="OCX" url="http://ohiolink.edu/EAD/oha.irk.html" countrycode="us">OCX0096</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>Guide to the John A. Richmond Scrapbook</titleproper>
<author>Anne Ryckbost</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt><publisher>Xavier University Archives and Special Collections</publisher><address><addressline>Xavier University, McDonald Library</addressline><addressline>1535 Musketeer Drive</addressline><addressline>Cincinnati, OH 45207-3341</addressline></address><date type="publication">2018</date></publicationstmt></filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded by Anne Ryckbost using the OhioLINK EAD Application in <date>2017</date></creation>
<langusage>English</langusage>
<descrules>Describing Archives: A Content Standard</descrules>
</profiledesc>
<revisiondesc><change><date normal="2018-02-06">2018-02-06</date><item>Added college students as subject heading</item></change></revisiondesc></eadheader>
<archdesc level="collection" type="inventory" relatedencoding="MARC">
<did>
<head>Overview of the Collection</head>
<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
<corpname>Xavier University Archives and Special Collections</corpname>
<address><addressline>Phone: 513-745-4821</addressline>
<addressline>http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives</addressline>
</address>
</repository>
<origination label="Creator:"><persname encodinganalog="100">Richmond, John A., 1883-1952</persname></origination>
<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">John A. Richmond Scrapbook</unittitle>
<physdesc label="Extent:" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>.88 linear feet (2 boxes)</extent></physdesc>
<abstract label="Abstract:" encodinganalog="520$a">Scrapbook of John A. Richmond (1883-1952), a student from Covington, Kentucky who graduated from Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio) in 1904. Scrapbook contains clippings, programs, invitations, photographs, and other ephemera from his time at Xavier, Georgetown University, and Harvard University. Topics include athletics, theater, student life, and commencement ceremonies. A few clippings document his professional life as the assistant city solicitor of Covington, Kentucky.</abstract>
<unitid encodinganalog="035" label="Collection Code" countrycode="us" repositorycode="OCX">XUA-95</unitid>
<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language:">The records are in <language langcode="eng">English</language></langmaterial>
<unitdate type="inclusive" label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f" normal="1890/1913" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1890-1913</unitdate></did>
<!-- TOP LEVEL METADATA GOES HERE: -->
<bioghist encodinganalog="545"><head>Biography of John A. Richmond</head><p>John Albert Richmond, son of Maurice J. Richmond and Annie Mahon, was born in 1883 in Covington, Kentucky. He attended Xavier University, known then as St. Xavier College, from approximately 1902-1904. While a student, he participated in the Philopedian Society, the St. Xavier Dramatic Club, and served as captain of the football team. He was also active in local amateur theater companies and track and field athletic competitions. After graduating from Xavier in 1904, he attended Georgetown University and received his master's in 1905. He then went to Harvard University for his law degree. He married Helen Rhinock in 1907 and they later divorced. Richmond returned to Covington, Kentucky serving as the assistant city solicitor and working as a lawyer. He died in 1952.</p><bioghist><p>Not specified</p></bioghist></bioghist><scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a"><head>Scope and Content</head><p>Scrapbook of John A. Richmond (1883-1952), a student  from Covington, Kentucky who graduated from Xavier University  (Cincinnati, Ohio) in 1904. The scrapbook contains clippings, programs,  invitations, photographs, and other ephemera from his time at Xavier, Georgetown, and Harvard universities as well as from his participation in local amateur theater. Topics include athletics,  theater, student life and conduct, and commencement ceremonies. There are programs from a field day sponsored by the Cincinnati Athletic Club in 1903 at which Richmond won or placed in several track events. There is also an 1890 program from La Salette Academy in Covington, Kentucky. A few clippings document Richmond's  professional life as the assistant city solicitor of Covington,  Kentucky. The photographs found loose in the back of the scrapbook include images of Richmond in his Xavier football uniform and a mounted card of Bishop John Baptist Purcell. There is also a postcard sent to Richmond from Paris in 1905 along with travel ephemera.</p><scopecontent><p>Not specified</p></scopecontent></scopecontent><arrangement encodinganalog="351$b"><head>Statement of Arrangement</head><p>Scrapbook maintained in its original order at collection level. Loose items found in back of scrapbook foldered separately.</p></arrangement><accessrestrict encodinganalog="506"><head>Restrictions on Access</head><p>Access to materials is by appointment only. Contact University Archives staff for an appointment.</p></accessrestrict><userestrict encodinganalog="540"><head>Restrictions on Use</head><p>This collection is the physical property of Xavier University. Copyright law of the United States governs the reproduction of copyrighted material. The User assumes full responsibility for the fair use of materials requested in total compliance with the copyright law of the United States that may arise through the use of any requested materials.</p></userestrict><prefercite encodinganalog="524"><head>Preferred Citation</head><p>Identification of item, Box Number, Folder number, XUA-95 John A. Richmond Scrapbook, Special Collections and University Archives, Xavier University Library, Cincinnati, Ohio</p></prefercite><acqinfo encodinganalog="541"><head>Acquisition Information</head><p>Scrapbook found in University Archives in 2017 without provenance information.</p></acqinfo><controlaccess><head>Indexing Terms</head><p>The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.</p><controlaccess><head>Subjects:</head><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Football</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">College theater</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Commencement ceremonies</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">College students</subject></controlaccess><controlaccess><head>Persons:</head><persname encodinganalog="600$a" source="local">Richmond, John A., 1883-1952</persname></controlaccess><controlaccess><head>Organizations/Corporations:</head><corpname encodinganalog="610$a" source="lcnaf">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="610$a" source="lcnaf">Georgetown University</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="610$a" source="local">La Salette Academy</corpname></controlaccess><controlaccess><head>Material Types:</head><genreform encodinganalog="655$a" source="gmgpc">Scrapbooks</genreform><genreform encodinganalog="655$a" source="lcgft">Photographic prints</genreform></controlaccess></controlaccess><dsc type="combined"><head>Detailed Description of The Collection</head><c01 level="item"><did><container type="Box">1-2</container><unittitle>John A. Richmond Scrapbook</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1890/1913" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1890-1913</unitdate></did></c01></dsc></archdesc>
</ead>