<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "http://www.library.kent.edu/ead.dtd">
<ead>
<eadheader findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="dublin core" repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601">
<eadid mainagencycode="OCX" url="http://ohiolink.edu/EAD/oha.irk.html" countrycode="us">OCX0048</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>Xavier University Acquisition of Edgecliff College records</titleproper>
<author>Tim McCabe</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt><publisher>Xavier University Archives and Special Collections</publisher><address><addressline>Xavier University, McDonald Library</addressline><addressline>1535 Musketeer Drive</addressline><addressline>Cincinnati, OH 45207-3341</addressline></address><date type="publication">2018</date></publicationstmt></filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded by Tim McCabe using the OhioLINK EAD Application in <date>2014</date></creation>
<langusage>English</langusage>
<descrules>Describing Archives: a Content Standard</descrules>
</profiledesc>
<revisiondesc><change><date normal="2014-10-01">October 1, 2014</date><item>Note on related materials added.</item></change><change><date normal="2014-11-19">November 19, 2014</date><item>Proper name entry revised to reflect LC standard</item></change><change><date normal="2017-11-06">2017-11-06</date><item>Material removed from binders and folders renumbered. Description updated, including acquisition information, scope and content, and folder titles.</item></change></revisiondesc></eadheader>
<archdesc level="collection" type="inventory" relatedencoding="MARC">
<did>
<head>Overview of the Collection</head>
<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
<corpname>Xavier University Archives and Special Collections</corpname>
<address><addressline>Phone: 513-745-4821</addressline>
<addressline>http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives</addressline>
</address>
</repository>
<origination label="Creator:"><corpname encodinganalog="110">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)</corpname></origination>
<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Xavier University Acquisition of Edgecliff College records</unittitle>
<physdesc label="Extent:" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>1 linear feet (3 boxes)</extent></physdesc>
<abstract label="Abstract:" encodinganalog="520$a">This is a collection of correspondence and related documents concerning the relationship of Edgecliff College and Xavier University from the Office of the Provost. The subject content deals chiefly with negotiations on the sale of Edgecliff to Xavier, on subsequent Xavier programming on the Edgecliff campus, and the eventual sale of the Edgecliff property by Xavier.</abstract>
<unitid encodinganalog="035" label="Collection Code" countrycode="us" repositorycode="OCX">XUA-48</unitid>
<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language:">The records are in <language langcode="eng">English</language></langmaterial>
<physloc label="Location:">Xavier University Archives, Cincinnati, Ohio</physloc><unitdate type="inclusive" label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f" normal="1967/1989" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1967-1989</unitdate></did>
<!-- TOP LEVEL METADATA GOES HERE: -->
<bioghist encodinganalog="545"><head>History of Xavier University Acquisiton of Edgecliff College</head><p>Xavier University purchased a three year option to purchase the Edgecliff College property in 1980. In 1983 the purchase was completed. In 1987 Xavier University sold the Edgecliff property but incorporated many of the Edgecliff academic programs into its curriculum.</p><bioghist><p>Originally called Our Lady of Cincinnati College at its founding in 1935 by the Sisters of Mercy, the college educated young women exclusively until 1970 when it opened its classrooms to men and adopted a new name, Edgecliff College. On July 1, 1980 Xavier University announced that it had purchased from the Sisters of Mercy a three year option to buy the Edgecliff campus property by June 30, 1983. Edgecliff College then became known as Edgecliff College of Xavier University, the fourth undergraduate college at Xavier University. In the spring of 1983 Xavier completed the purchase of the Edgecliff property from the Sisters of Mercy.  In April 1987 Xavier University sold the Edgecliff property. Academic programming was transferred to the main Xavier campus that year. Edgecliff's departments of art, music, and theatre arts joined the College of Arts and Sciences, while its departments of nursing and social work were incorporated into Xavier's new College of Professional Studies.</p></bioghist></bioghist><scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a"><head>Scope and Content</head><p>This collection gives a picture of the negotiations leading to the purchase of Edgecliff College by Xavier University and subsequent transitional activities during and after the purchase process. Included in the collection are correspondence files of various academic vice presidents. Both the purchase agreement of 1983 and the sale agreement of 1987 are included in this collection.</p><scopecontent><p>Not specified</p></scopecontent></scopecontent><arrangement encodinganalog="351$b"><head>Statement of Arrangement</head><p>The collection is arranged in these general categories:</p><list type="simple"><item>Correspondence Files</item><item>Transitional Topics (Committees, Academic Programs, etc.)</item><item>Legal Documents</item></list></arrangement><accessrestrict encodinganalog="506"><head>Restrictions on Access</head><p>Restricted access. Please contact the Xavier University Archives staff.</p></accessrestrict><prefercite encodinganalog="524"><head>Preferred Citation</head><p>Box Number, Folder Number, XUA-48, Xavier University Acquisition of Edgecliff College records, Special Collections and University Archives, Xavier University Library, Cincinnati, Ohio.</p></prefercite><acqinfo encodinganalog="541"><head>Acquisition Information</head><p>Transfer from the Office of the Administrative Vice President, XUA2008-11.</p></acqinfo><custodhist encodinganalog="561"><head>Custodial History</head><p>These records were transferred to University Archives from the Office of the Administrative Vice President and principal assistant to the president (transfer, XUA2008-11). This office currently manages property acquisition for the university. Much of the correspondence files was originally held in the Office of the Xavier University Academic Vice President, know known as the Office of the Provost and Chief Academic Officer.</p></custodhist><controlaccess><head>Indexing Terms</head><p>The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.</p><controlaccess><head>Subjects:</head><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Edgecliff College</subject><subject encodinganalog="650$a" source="lcsh">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)--Administration</subject></controlaccess><controlaccess><head>Organizations/Corporations:</head><corpname encodinganalog="710$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). Office of the Provost and Chief Academic Officer</corpname></controlaccess></controlaccess><dsc type="combined"><head>Detailed Description of The Collection</head><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">1-7</container><unittitle>Edgecliff Related Correspondence of Xavier Academic Vice Presidents (Brennan; Minahan; Fortin)</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1967/1987" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1967-1987</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This is a correspondence file maintained by various Xavier University Academic Vice Presidents and relating to Xavier University's relationship with Edgecliff College and the eventual acquisition of Edgecliff by Xavier. Included in the file is correspondence, with related documents, from and to Francis C. Brennan, S.J., Dr. John P. Minahan and Dr. Roger Fortin. Correspondence of Dr. Roger Fortin acting as Dean of Edgecliff College of Xavier University is also found.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">8-14</container><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>Edgecliff Negotiations Correspondence File (Brennan)</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1977 May 1" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1977 May 1</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" 1979-1980" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1979-1980</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This correspondence file of Francis C. Brennan, S.J., Xavier University Academic Vice President, deals with the negotiations between officials of Edgecliff College and Xavier University regarding the acquisition of Edgecliff by Xavier University. Included are copies of correspondence of the Xavier University president Robert W. Mulligan, S.J.. Related documents are included in the file.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>College of Professional Studies Xavier University Academic Vice Presidents Correspondence</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1984/1988" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1984-1988</unitdate></did></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>Edgecliff Task Force</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1981/1983" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1981-1983</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" undated" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> undated</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>The mission of the Edgecliff Task Force was to make a recommendation to the Xavier Board of Trustees concerning "finalizing the Edgecliff College acquisition...More specifically, ....to address...1) the feasibility of increasing the enrollment in existing programs and developing new enrollments in new credit and non-credit programs on the Edgecliff Campus; 2) the feasibility of developing additional revenue through summer rental of Edgecliff facilities; 3) the cost and feasibility of reproducing current Edgecliff programs on the main campus (as a means of assessing the value of Edgecliff programs within the University); 4) the feasibility of alternate ...methods of meeting all or part of the acquisition costs." (see Currie memo of 9/29/1982 to the Task Force)</p></scopecontent><relatedmaterial><p>The Xavier University Archives also has materials on the Edgecliff Campus Coordinating Committee found in XUA-36, Xavier University inactive committee records (Box 1, Folder 8).</p></relatedmaterial></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">4</container><unittitle>Edgecliff Outreach Task Force</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1982/1986" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1982-1986</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This was a committee headed by Robert W. Schmidt, S.J.. Its purpose was to foster relationships between Edgecliff College and the local community. Correspondence originated in the office files of Academic Vice President Dr. John Minahan.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>Edgecliff Negotiations: Clippings and Correspondence</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1979/1981" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1979-1981</unitdate></did></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>Edgecliff Property Sale: Memos to the Xavier Community</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1986/1987" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1986-1987</unitdate></did></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>Tuition Remissions Xavier Academic Vice Presidents Correspondence File</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1980/1989" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1980-1989</unitdate></did></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">4-7</container><unittitle>Edgecliff College Purchase Agreement and Related Documents</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1983" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1983</unitdate></did></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">8-10</container><unittitle>Edgecliff Property Sale Agreement and Related Documents</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1987" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1987</unitdate></did></c01></dsc></archdesc>
</ead>