<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "http://www.library.kent.edu/ead.dtd">
<ead>
<eadheader findaidstatus="edited-full-draft" langencoding="iso639-2b" relatedencoding="dublin core" repositoryencoding="iso15511" countryencoding="iso3166-1" dateencoding="iso8601">
<eadid mainagencycode="OCX" url="http://ohiolink.edu/EAD/oha.irk.html" countrycode="us">OCX0088</eadid>
<filedesc>
<titlestmt>
<titleproper>Annual Reports to the President collection</titleproper>
<author>Finding aid prepared by Thomas Kennealy, S.J.</author>
</titlestmt>
<publicationstmt><publisher>Xavier University Archives and Special Collections</publisher><address><addressline>Xavier University, McDonald Library</addressline><addressline>3800 Victory Parkway</addressline><addressline>Cincinnati, OH 45207</addressline></address><date type="publication">2017</date></publicationstmt></filedesc>
<profiledesc>
<creation>Finding aid encoded by Tim McCabe using the OhioLINK EAD Application in <date>2016</date></creation>
<langusage>English</langusage>
<descrules>Describing Archives: a Content Standard</descrules>
</profiledesc>
</eadheader>
<archdesc level="collection" type="inventory" relatedencoding="MARC">
<did>
<head>Overview of the Collection</head>
<repository label="Repository:" encodinganalog="852$a">
<corpname>Xavier University Archives and Special Collections</corpname>
<address><addressline>Phone: 513-745-4821</addressline>
<addressline>http://www.xavier.edu/cm/archives</addressline>
</address>
</repository>
<origination label="Creator:"><corpname encodinganalog="110">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio). President's Office</corpname></origination>
<unittitle label="Title:" encodinganalog="245$a">Annual Reports to the President collection</unittitle>
<physdesc label="Extent:" encodinganalog="300$a"><extent>2.25 linear feet (5 boxes)</extent></physdesc>
<abstract label="Abstract:" encodinganalog="520$a">This is a collection of annual reports sent to the President of Xavier University by various divisions, colleges, departments, offices, clubs and programs on campus. Each year may reflect a different mix of reporting units.</abstract>
<unitid encodinganalog="035" label="Collection Code" countrycode="us" repositorycode="OCX">XUA-87</unitid>
<langmaterial encodinganalog="546" label="Language:">The records are in <language langcode="eng">English</language></langmaterial>
<physloc label="Location:">Xavier University Archives, Cincinnati, Ohio</physloc><unitdate type="inclusive" label="Dates:" encodinganalog="245$f" normal="1950/1995" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1950-1995</unitdate></did>
<!-- TOP LEVEL METADATA GOES HERE: -->
<bioghist encodinganalog="545"><head>History of Annual Reports to the President</head><p>Beginning in the early 1950's it became the custom for every division, college, school, department, committee, office and student club or activity of the university to submit an annual report to the president in late May or early June. These reports summarized activities for the academic year just ended.</p><bioghist><p>These reports were usually prepared and sent to the president by the following individuals: for University Divisions: the appropriate vice-president; for Colleges and Schools: the dean; for Academic Departments: the departmental chair; for University Committees: the committee chair; for Offices and Centers: the Director of the office or center; for Student Clubs, Activities, Publications, Fraternities: the Faculty moderator or advisor.</p></bioghist></bioghist><scopecontent encodinganalog="520$a"><head>Scope and Content</head><p>This is a collection of reports sent to the President of Xavier University. These reports reflect activities and developments for the year within various organizational entities on campus. This collection is very incomplete. There are no reports  for several years.</p><scopecontent/></scopecontent><arrangement encodinganalog="351$b"><head>Statement of Arrangement</head><p>This collection is arranged chronologically.</p></arrangement><relatedmaterial encodinganalog="544 1"><head>Related Material</head><p>For other reports submitted to the President see XUA-8, the Xavier University Annual Reports collection.</p></relatedmaterial><accessrestrict encodinganalog="506"><head>Restrictions on Access</head><p>Some materials may have restricted access. Please contact the archives staff.</p></accessrestrict><prefercite encodinganalog="524"><head>Preferred Citation</head><p>Box Number, Folder Number, XUA-87, Annual Reports to the President collection, Special Collections and Archives, Xavier University, Cincinnati, Ohio.</p></prefercite><acqinfo encodinganalog="541"><head>Acquisition Information</head><p>These materials have been acquired from various sources.</p></acqinfo><controlaccess><head>Indexing Terms</head><p>The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.</p><controlaccess><head>Organizations/Corporations:</head><corpname encodinganalog="610$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)-- Administration</corpname><corpname encodinganalog="610$a" source="local">Xavier University (Cincinnati, Ohio)-- Planning</corpname></controlaccess></controlaccess><dsc type="combined"><head>Detailed Description of The Collection</head><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>1950 to 1953: Academic Departments</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1951/1953" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1951-1953</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains reports from the Department of Mathematics and Physics.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>1953-1954: Divisions, Colleges, Academic Departments</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1953/1954" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1953-1954</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains reports from the following academic divisions, colleges, schools or departments: Accounting, Biology, Chemistry, Classics, College of Liberal Arts, Economics and Business, Education, English, Evening Division, Graduate Division, History and Political Science, Mathematics and Physics, Modern Languages, Philosophy, Physical Education, and Psychology.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>1953-1954: Committees, Offices, Student Clubs</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1954" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1954</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports: University Committees:    Academic Rank and Tenure Committee, Fine Arts Committee, Scholarship Committee, Student Welfare Committee;</p><p>University Offices, Centers, Residence Halls:   Admissions Office, Alumnae Association, Alumni Association, Athletic Department, Band Department, Book Lovers Association, Book Store, Bursar, Cafeteria and South Hall, Dads Club, Guidance and Placement Office, Grounds, Department of Housing, Elet Hall, Library, Musketeer Club, News Bureau, Office of the Dean of Men, Placement Office, Veterans Affairs, Registrar, Summer Sessions;</p><p>Student Clubs, Activities, Publications and Fraternities:  Accounting Society, Alpha Sigma Nu Honorary Fraternity, Athenaeum Magazine, Biology Club, Chicago Club, Clef Club, Debating Society, Confederate Club and Economics Club, Family Life Institute, French Club, Heidelberg Club, Masque Society, Mermaid Tavern, N.F.C.C.S., Political Forum, Psychology Club, Rifle Club, Sailing Club, Sodality and Religious Welfare, Spanish Club, Student Activities, Student Council, "Xavier Presents" TV Show, Xavier University News.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">4</container><unittitle>1954-1955: Divisions, Colleges, Academic Departments, Committees</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1955" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1955</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>Academic Divisions, Colleges, Schools and Departments:   Accounting, Biology and Biology Club, Classical Languages, Economics and Business, Education, English, Evening Division, Graduate Division, History and Political Science, Mathematics, Military Science, Modern Languages, Philosophy, Physical Education and Intramurals, Psychology, Physics, Theology;</p><p>University Committees: Fine Arts Committee, Rank and Tenure Committee, Scholarship Committee, Student Welfare Committee.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">5</container><unittitle>1954-1955: Offices and Student Clubs</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1955" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1955</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>University Offices, Centers and Residence Halls:    Admissions Office, Alumni Association, Athletic Department, Office of the Business Manager, Office of the Dean of Men, Food Service Department, Guidance Center, Housing Department, Library, Musketeer Club, News Bureau, Placement Office, Public Relations, Registrar, Student Counselor, Summer Sessions, Treasurer's Office, Veterans' Office;</p><p>Student Clubs, Activities, Publications and Fraternities:    Accounting Society, Alchemists Club, Alpha Sigma Nu Honorary Fraternity, Apostleship of Prayer, Athenaeum, Athletic Review, Band Department, Buckeye Club, Chicago Club, Cleveland Club, Confederate Club, Delta Nu Alpha Transportation Fraternity Chapter, Dormitory Council, Family Life Institute, French Club, Heidelberg Club, Hoosier Club, Maria Della Strada Sodality, Masque Society, Mermaid Tavern, Musketeer Yearbook, National Federation of Catholic College Students, Philosophy Club, Pittsburgh Club, Political Forum, Psychology Club, Sailing Club, Sodalities, Spanish Club, Student Activities, Student Council, Xavier University News.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">6</container><unittitle>1955-1956: Divisions, Colleges, Academic Departments</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1956" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1956</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>University Divisions, Colleges, Schools and Departments:    Accounting, Biology, Business Administration, Chemistry, Classical Languages, Economics and Business, English, Evening Division, History and Political Science, Institute of Hispanic Studies, Mathematics, Military Department, Modern Languages, Philosophy, Physical Education and Intramurals, Physics, Psychology, Theology.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">7</container><unittitle>1955-1956: Committees, Offices</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1956" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1956</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>University Committees:    Fine Arts Committee, Student Welfare Committee;</p><p>University Offices, Centers, and Residence Halls:    Admissions Office, Alumnae Association, Alumni Association, Athletic Department, Bookstore and Post Office, Buildings and Grounds, Bursar, Business Manager, Office of Dean of Men, Office of Development, Food Services Department, Guidance Center, Heidelberg Club, Housing, Library, Maintenance Department, Musketeer Club, Placement Office, Department of Public Relations, Publications, Registrar, Student Counselor, Student Services, Summer Sessions, Treasurer's Office, Veterans' Office.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">1</container><container type="Folder">8</container><unittitle>1955-1956: Student Clubs and Activities</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1956" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1956</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>Student Clubs, Activities, Publications, and Fraternities:    Accounting Society, Alchemyst Club, Apostleship of Prayer, Athenaeum, Band Department, Booklovers Association, Buckeye Club, Chicago Club, Clef Club, Cleveland Club, Dads Club, Delta Nu Alpha Transportation Fraternity Chapter, Dormitory Council, French Club, Indiana Club, Maria Della Strada Sodality, Masque Society, Mermaid Tavern, Musketeer Yearbook, National Federation of Catholic College Students, Political Forum, Psychology Club, Sailing Club, Sodalities, Spanish Club, Student Council, Student Directory, Swimming Team, Veterans' Club, "Xavier Presents" TV Show, Xavier University News.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>1956-1957: Divisions, Colleges, Schools, Academic Departments</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1957" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1957</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>Academic Divisions, Colleges, Schools and Departments:    Accounting, Biology, Business Administration, Classical Languages, College of Arts and Sciences, Economics, English, Evening Division, Graduate School, History and Political Science, Institute of Hispanic Studies, Mathematics, Military Department, Modern Languages, Physical Education and Intramurals, Physics, Psychology, Theology.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>1956-1957: Committees, Offices, Student Activities</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1957" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1957</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>University Committees:    Budget Committee, Fine Arts Committee, Scholarship Committee, Student Welfare Committee;</p><p>University Offices, Centers, and Residence Halls:    Alumnae Association, Alumni Association, Athletic Department, Bellarmine Chapel, Bursar's Office, Business Manager's Office, Development Office, Food Service Department, Guidance Center, Library, Musketeer Club, News Bureau, Placement Office, Department of Public Relations, Office of Publications, Student Counselor, Summer Sessions, Treasurer's Office, Veterans' Counselor Office;</p><p>Student Clubs, Activities, Publications and Fraternities:    Accounting Society, Alchemyst Club, Alpha Sigma Nu Honorary Fraternity, Apostleship of Prayer, Athenaeum, Band Department, Biology Club, Booklovers Association, Bowling League, Buckeye Club, Camera Club, Chesterton Club, Chicago Club, Clef Club, Cleveland Club, Confederate Club, Delta Nu Alpha Transportation Fraternity, Eastern Club, Economics Club, Family Life Club, Flying Club, Heidelberg Club, Garraghan History Club, Housing Office, Indiana Club, Maria Della Strada Sodality, Masque Society, Mermaid Tavern, Musketeer Yearbook, National Federation of Catholic College Students, Natural Law Society, Operation Youth, Physics Club, Psychology Club, Sailing Club,Sodalities, Spanish Club, Student Council, Vererans' Club, "Xavier Presents" TV Show, Xavier University News.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>1957-1958: Divisions, Colleges, Schools, Academic Departments</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1958" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1958</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>Academic Divisions, Colleges, Schools and Departments:    Accounting, Biology, Business Administration, Chemistry, Classical Languages, College of Arts and Sciences, Evening Division, Graduate School, History and Political Science, Institute of Hispanic Studies, Hospital Administration Program, Mathematics, Military Department, Physics, Psychology, Theology.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">4</container><unittitle>1957-1958: Committees, Offices</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1958" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1958</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>University Committees:    Advanced Placement Committee, Budget Committee, Faculty Committee, Pre-Medical Committee, Rank and Tenure Committee, Research and Advanced Study Committee, Scholarship Committee;</p><p>University Offices, Centers and Residence Halls:    Admissions Office, Alumni Association, Athletics Business Manager, Athletics Publicity Office, Bellarmine Chapel, Booklovers Association, Bursar's Office, Office of the Business Manager, Dads Club, Office of Dean of Men and Director of Housing, Family Life Institute, Food Service Department, Guidance and Measurement Office, Library, Marion Hall, Musketeer Club, News Bureau, Placement Office, Department of Public Relations, Publication Advertising, Society for the Advancement of Management, Student Counselor, Treasurer's Office, Veterans' Office.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">5</container><unittitle>1957-1958: Student Clubs and Activities</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1958" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1958</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>Student Clubs, Activities, Publications and Fraternities:    (Memo on Club Moderators), Accounting Society, Alchemyst Club, Alpha Signa Nu Honorary Fraternity, Athenaeum, Band Department, Biology Club, Buckeye Club, Camera Club, Cleveland Club, Dormitory Council, Eastern Club, Flying Club, Heidelberg Club, Indiana Club, Intramural Sports, Masque Society, Mermaid Tavern, National Federation of Catholic College Students, Natural Law Society, Psychology Club, Sailing Club, Sodalities, Spanish Club, Student Activities, Student Fine Arts Committee, "The Sure Party," Toledo Club, Veterans' Club, Xavier News.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">2</container><container type="Folder">6</container><unittitle>1958-1959: Divisions, Colleges, Schools, Academic Departments</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1959" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1959</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>Detailed summary of the annual reports for this year and a list of departmental chairs.</p><p>Academic Divisions, Colleges, Schools and Departments:    Accounting, Biology, Business Administration, Chemistry, Classical Languages, College of Arts and Sciences, Economics, Education, English and Speech Arts, Evening Division, Graduate School, Hospital Administration, Institute of Hispanic Studies, Mathematics, Military Department, Modern Languages, Philosophy, Physics, Psychology, Theology.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>1958-1959: Committees, Offices</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1959" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1959</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>University Committees:    Advanced Placement Committee, Faculty Committee, Fine Arts Committee, Honors Course Committee/ Mardi Gras, Measurement and Placement Committee, Pre-Legal Committee, Pre-Medical Committee, Rank and Tenure Committee, Registration Committee, Research and Advanced Study Committee, Scholarship Committee, Student Welfare Committee;</p><p>University Offices, Centers and Residence Halls:    Admissions Office and Dads Club, Alumnae Association, Alumni Association, Athletic Department, Bellarmine Chapel, Brockman Hall, Booklovers' Association, Department of Buildings and Grounds, Bookstore, Office of Bursar, Office of Business Manager, Office of Dean of Men, Office of Development, Food Service Department, Guidance Center, Marion Hall, Honors Hall, Institute of Business Services, Office of Housing, Library, Maria Della Strada Sodality, Mermaid Tavern, News Bureau, Placement Office, Department of Public Relations, Office of Publications, Registrar's Office, Student Counselor, Summer Sessions, Treasurer's Office, Veterans' Office.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>1958-1959: Student Activities</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1959" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1959</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>Student Clubs, Activities, Publications and Fraternities:    Accounting Society, Alchemyst Club, Alpha Sigma Nu Honorary Fraternity, Apostleship of Prayer, Athenaeum, Band Department, Biology Club, Bowling Club, Buckeye Club, Cheerleaders, Chesterton Society/ Philosophical Society, Chicago Club, Clef Club, Cleveland Club, Detroit Club, Dormitory Council, Eastern Club, Indiana Club, Flying Club, Heidelberg Club, Jazz Club, Council of Knights of Columbus, Natural Law Society, National Federation of Catholic College Students, Sailing Club, Society for Advancement of Management, Sodalities, Spanish Club, Student Council, Student Fine Arts Committee, Swimming Club, Veterans' Club, Xavier University News, Xiles (Evening Division).</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>1959-1960: Divisions, Colleges, Schools, Academic Departments</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1960" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1960</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>A summary of the pertinent points from the annual reports of this year. A list of departmental chairs and moderators of clubs for this year.</p><p>Academic Divisions, Colleges, Schools and Departments:    Accounting, Biology, Business Administration, Chemistry, Classical Languages, College of Arts and Sciences, Economics, English and Speech, Evening Division, History and Political Science, Hospital Administration Program, Institute of Hispanic Studies, Mathematics, Military Department, Modern Languages, Philosophy, Physics and Seismology, Psychology, Theology.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">4</container><unittitle>1959-1960: Committees</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1960" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1960</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>University Committees:    Advanced Placement Committee, Faculty Committee, Fine Arts Committee, Honors Course Committee/ Mardi Gras, Non-Academic Personnel Committee, Pre-Engineering Committee, Pre-Legal Committee, Pre-Medical Committee, Rank and Tenure Committee, Registration Committee, Religious Welfare Committee, Research and Advanced Study Committee, Student Welfare Committee.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">5</container><unittitle>1959-1960: Offices, Centers, Residence Halls</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1960" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1960</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>University Offices, Centers and Residence Halls:    Admissions Office, Alumnae Association, Alumni Association, Alumni and Faculty Sodality, Athletics Department, Bellarmine Chapel, Booklovers' Association, Bookstore (missing), Department of Buildings and Grounds, Office of Bursar, Dads Club, Office of Dean of Men, Office of Development, Elet Hall, Family Life Institute, Food Service Department, Guidance Center, Health Center, Office of Housing, Institute of Business Services, International Students, Library, Maria della Strada Sodality, Marion Hall/ Honors Hall, Placement Office, Office of Registrar, Student Activities, Summer Sessions, Treasurer's Office, University Chaplain Office, Veterans' Office.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">6</container><unittitle>1959-1960: Student Activities</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1960" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1960</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>Student Clubs, Activities, Publications and Fraternities:    Accounting Society, Alchemyst Club, Alpha Sigma Nu Honorary Fraternity, Apostleship of Prayer, Athenaeum, Band Department, Biology Club, Bowling Club, Bridge Club, Brockman Hall, Chesterton Philosophy Club, Chicago Club, Clef Club, Detroit Club, Dormitory Council, Economics Club, Elet Hall, Flying Club, Foreign Studies Club, French Club, Heidelberg Club, Indiana Club, Intramural Athletics, Jazz Club, Council of Knights of Columbus, Masque Society, Mermaid Tavern, Natural Law Society, News Bureau, Physics Club, Sailing Club, Society for Advancement of Management, Sodalities, Spanish Club, Student Council, Student Directory, Student Fine arts Committee, Toledo Club, Veterans' Club, "Xavier Presents" TV Show, Xavier University News.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">7</container><unittitle>1960-1965: Department of Physics</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1961/1965" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1961-1965</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>Academic Departments:    Department of Physics annual reports, from Academic Year 1960-61 through Academic Year 1964-65.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">8</container><unittitle>1965-1967: Divisions and Academic Departments</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1966/1967" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1966-1967</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>For 1965-1966: Department of Education, Department of Physics</p><p>For 1966-1967: Academic Vice President (Academic Council, Admissions Committee, Dean's Office, Rank and Tenure Committee), Department of Physics</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">3</container><container type="Folder">9</container><unittitle>1967-1969: Academic Divisions, Committees and Departments</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1968/1969" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1968-1969</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>For 1967-1968:  Academic Vice President (Academic Affairs, Academic Council Committee, Rank and Tenure Committee), Department of Physics and Supplement (including the Report of the Tri-State Research Institute), Ad Hoc Committee on Research;</p><p>For 1968-1969: Academic Vice President (Academic Affairs, Academic Council Committee, Rank and Tenure Committee), Department of Physics.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">4</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>1969-1971: Academic Divisions and Departments</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1970/1971" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1970-1971</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>For 1969-1970: Academic Vice President (Office of Academic Vice President, Academic Council, Rank and Tenure Committee), Department of Physics;</p><p>For 1970-1971: Academic Vice President (Office of Academic Vice President, Academic Council, Rank and Tenure Committee), Evening College and Summer Sessions, University and Urban Affairs Office, Department of Physics.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">4</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>1971-1973: Academic Divisions and Departments</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1972/1973" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1972-1973</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>For 1971-1972: Academic Vice President (Office of the Academic Vice President, Academic Council, Rank and Tenure Committee), College of Business Administration, Evening College and Summer Sessions, Department of Philosophy;</p><p>For 1972-1973: Academic Vice President (Rank and Tenure Committee, Academic Coordinating Council, Budget Committee).</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">4</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>1973-1974: Departments, Committees, Offices</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1974" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1974</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>Divisions, Colleges, Schools and Departments:    Biology, Business-Finance and Treasurer, Classics, College of Arts and Sciences, College of Business Administration, Center for Student Development, Communication Arts, Graduate Corrections Program, Economics and Finance, Education, English, History and Political Science, Management and Industrial Relations, Mathematics, Military Science, Modern Languages, Philosophy, Psychology, Theology;</p><p>University Committees:    Health Sciences Committee, Library Committee;</p><p>University Offices:    Admissions and Recruitment, Institute for Business and Community Services, Registrar.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">4</container><container type="Folder">4</container><unittitle>1974-1981: Departments, Colleges, Committees</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1975/1981" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1975-1981</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>For 1974-1975: Divisions, Colleges, Schools and Departments:    Biology, College of Business Administration, College of Continuing Education, Communication Arts, Economics and Industrial Relations, Graduate School, Physics, Psychology, Summer Sessions; Committees:    Health Sciences Committee, Institute for Business and Community Services;</p><p>For 1976-1977: Vice President for Administration;</p><p>For 1978-1979: Academic Vice President, Accounting and Finance Department, College of Business Administration, College of Continuing Education, Financial Aid Office, History, Library, Management and Information Systems;</p><p>For 1979-1980:  College of Business Administration;</p><p>For 1980-1981: College of Business Administration, Nursing.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">4</container><container type="Folder">5</container><unittitle>1981-1982: Divisions, Colleges, Offices</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1982" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1982</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>Divisions, Colleges, and Schools:     College of Arts and Sciences, College of Business Administration, College of Business Administration (Undergraduate), College of Continuing Education, Edgecliff College, Graduate School, Summer School;</p><p>Offices, Centers and Residence Halls:    Academic Computing, Center for Management and Professional Development, Library, Registrar.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">4</container><container type="Folder">6</container><unittitle>1981-1982: Academic Departments</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1982" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1982</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>Academic Departments:    Accounting and Finance, Art, Biology, Chemistry, Classical Languages, Communication Arts, Consumer Science, Graduate Corrections Program, Economics and Industrial Relations, Education, English, History, Hospital and Health Administration, Management and Information Systems, Marketing, Mathematics, Music, Modern Languages, Philosophy, Physics, Political Science and Sociology, Psychology, Public Administration, Social Work, Theatre Arts, Theology.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">4</container><container type="Folder">7</container><unittitle>1982-1983: Academic Divisions and Departments</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1983" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1983</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>Divisions, Colleges, Schools and Departments:    Accounting, Art, Biology, Chemistry, Classical Languages, College of Continuing Education and Summer Sessions, Communication Arts, Criminal Justice, Economics and Industrial Relations, Education, English, History, Hospital and Health Administration, Management and Information Systems, Marketing, Mathematics and Computer Science, Military Science, Modern Languages, Music, Nursing, Philosophy, Physics, Political Science and Sociology, Psychology, Social Work, Theatre Arts, Theology.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">4</container><container type="Folder">8</container><unittitle>1982-1983: University Offices</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1983" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1983</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>Offices and Centers:    Academic Bridge, Academic Computing, Bureau of Governmental Research and Service, Center for Management and Professional Development, Library, Registrar.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">5</container><container type="Folder">1</container><unittitle>1983-1984: Divisions, Colleges</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1984" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1984</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>Academic Affairs, College of Arts and Sciences, College of Business Administration, College of Continuing Education.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">5</container><container type="Folder">2</container><unittitle>1984-1985: Divisions, Colleges, Offices</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1985" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1985</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>Academic Affairs (Vice President for Academic Affairs), College of Arts and Sciences, College of Business Administration, College of Professional Studies, Division of Continuing Education, Registrar, Report on the Use of the Computer System at Xavier University.</p></scopecontent></c01><c01 level="file"><did><container type="Box">5</container><container type="Folder">3</container><unittitle>1985-1995: Divisions and Offices</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1986" era="ce" calendar="gregorian">1986</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" 1988" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1988</unitdate><unitdate type="inclusive" normal=" 1995" era="ce" calendar="gregorian"> 1995</unitdate></did><scopecontent><p>This folder contains the following annual reports:</p><p>for 1985-1986: University Relations;</p><p>for 1987-1988: Libraries;</p><p>for 1994-1995: Faculty Committee.</p></scopecontent></c01></dsc></archdesc>
</ead>